<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the day of grace, or, A discourse concerning the possibility and fear of its being past before death shewing the groundless doubts, and mistaken apprehensions of some as to their being finally forsaken and left of God, with the dangerous symptomsand approaches of others to such a sad state, in four sermons from Psalm LXXX1. 11, 12 / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3679A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369675</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">188136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2856:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the day of grace, or, A discourse concerning the possibility and fear of its being past before death shewing the groundless doubts, and mistaken apprehensions of some as to their being finally forsaken and left of God, with the dangerous symptomsand approaches of others to such a sad state, in four sermons from Psalm LXXX1. 11, 12 / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 141, [1] p., 1 leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abraham Chandler and are to be sold by John Butler in Worcester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains portrait frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Publisher advertisements at end: p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXI 11, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of John Shower</figDesc>
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: John Shower</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:3"/>
            <p>Of The Day of Grace: OR, A DISCOURSE Concerning The Poſſibility, and Fear of its being Paſt, before Death.</p>
            <p>SHEWING The groundleſs Doubts, and miſtaken Apprehenſions of Some, as to their being finally Forſaken, and left of God. With the Dangerous Symptoms and Approaches of Others to ſuch a ſad State.</p>
            <p>In Four SERMONS From <hi>Pſalm</hi> LXXXI. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abraham Chandler,</hi> and to be Sold by <hi>John Butler</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe following Sermons were preacht-at the Earneſt Deſire of an unknown Perſon ſent me in a Letter, expreſſing a more than ordinary Concern and Fear, lest <hi>the day of Grace</hi> ſhould be past, and the Holy Spirit finally departed, ſo as to Return and Strive no more. Many <hi>Upright Chriſtians</hi> after aggravated Backſlidings, or under Great Temptations, or in deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy are apt to conclude thus hardly of themſelves. Such as theſe I have endeavour'd to Convince, that this is not the state of their Caſe, or ever like to be.</p>
            <p>I have alſo ſhown, <hi>who</hi> have reaſon to Apprehend themſelves in Danger of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Text. For 'tis poſſible, and more than poſſible, that after long Reſistance and Obſtinacy, God may Judicially let Men <hi>Alone,</hi> and give 'em over. Though their Lives be prolonged, they may be ſealed up to Wrath, and reſerved to Judgment. <hi>Four Generations</hi> filled the Meaſure of the <hi>Amorites</hi> Sin, though <hi>five</hi> paſt before they were deſtroyed. And though <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s
<pb facs="tcp:188136:5"/>time expir'd, 'tis thought, at <hi>the Sixth Plague,</hi> God upheld and harden'd him, (principally by ſuffering him to harden him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) till the <hi>Tenth</hi> was paſt. The ſins of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> were full at the Murder of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> but they were not deſtroyed till <hi>forty years</hi> after.</p>
            <p>I muſt Confeſs, that we cannot tell poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively when this is true concerning any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon: Nor is any man bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it concerning <hi>Himſelf;</hi> but is <hi>alway</hi> obliged to believe, that if he do truly Repent, he ſhall find Mercy. For though <hi>God</hi> may preſcribe Limits to his own Grace, <hi>we</hi> ought not to bound it. Shall any man ſay, Divine Patience hath waited on me, (or on ſuch a one ſo long,) it <hi>can</hi> wait <hi>no longer.</hi> Such <hi>Deſpair</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Grace, while in the uſe of God's Appointed Means, is very <hi>Inſolent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi> You are obliged, (as a Thing highly grateful to him) <hi>to Hope in his Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, whatever your Doubts and Fears are, if you firmly purpoſe to go on in the Way which leads to Life: if you will not turn a ſide from following the Lord; if you Reſolve, <hi>Come what will of it, I will never give over praying, ſeeking, ſtriving, wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let him do what he will with me, I'le not deſiſt; I'le run after
<pb facs="tcp:188136:5"/>him, I'le fly to him, I'le call upon him, as long as I live,</hi> &amp;c. A Bleſſing from the <hi>Author</hi> and Purchaſer of all Grace may be undoubtedly expected by ſuch a one. <hi>Prov 8.34.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, watching daily at my Gates, waiting at the Poſts of my Doors. For whoſo findeth me, findeth Life.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>If you hear him, and wait,
<note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>O.</hi> Meditations and Diſcourſes of the Glory of Chriſt, applyed to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted Sinners, <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> p. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> (ſaith Dr.</hi> O) <hi>though you have not yet Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, but are kept at the Gates and Poſts of the Doors, yet in the Iſſue you ſhall be Bleſſed. The rule in this Caſe is,</hi> Hoſ. <hi>6.3.</hi> Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know. <hi>Are you in the way of knowing Chriſt in the uſe of means, hearing the Word, and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Endeavors in Holy Duties; though you cannot yet attain unto any Evidence, that you have received him, have cloſed with him,</hi> (nay tho you queſtion whether ever he will Receive you,) Nothing can R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine you but giving over the way wherein you are; <hi>for then ſhall you know, if you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low on to know the Lord.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:6"/>
            <p>Theſe Diſcourſes are printed almoſt <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim</hi> as preacht; which I hope will rather promote, than leſſen their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs unto Such, who are moſt like to read <hi>'em,</hi> and to whoſe Caſe they are moſt ſuited. The Day of Reckoning is near; Death and Judgment are at hand: May I then find mercy of the Lord! Give an Account of my Stewardſhip with Comfort! And be found in Chriſt to the Glory of God. Beg it for me; as I do and ſhall thy profiting by this, and all the many other Helps to further thy Salvation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons_on_Psalm_n81">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:188136:6"/>
            <head>Four SERMONS ON Pſalm LXXXI. 11, 12.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The Firſt Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. LXXXI. 11, 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But my People would not hearken to my Voice, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> would none of me, ſo I gave them up to their own Hearts luſts: and they walked in their own Counſels.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE <hi>Jews</hi> have a Tradition, that at ſtated times of the year God doth lament and complaine over their ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that <hi>Temple</hi> that was once the Seat of his Glory, and the Place of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:188136:7"/>ſpecial Reſidence for ſo long a time. Their own Value, and affection for it, made them fondly imagine, that God himſelf could not behold its Aſhes and Diſſolution without Reſentment: Not conſidering that the Wickedneſs of the People called by his Name, and entruſted with the Priviledges of his Houſe, had provoked his moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeverity to lay it waſte. This was a weak and groundleſs Fancy of the carnal <hi>Jews:</hi> We have other Meaſures whereby to Judge of the bleſſed God. We are fully aſſured that his Thoughts are not as ours in ſuch matters; That it is a far ſadder ſpectacle in his Eye, to behold the Hypocriſy and Carnali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe that worſhip in his <hi>Temple,</hi> than to ſee it laid in Ruines; a far more diſmal ſight, to behold the offers of his Grace refuſed, and ſlighted; to have the Invitations of the Goſpel, and the glad Tidings of Peace reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by thoſe who can be ſaved no other Way; and who muſt periſh if they neglect this great Salvation: To ſee Multitudes of <hi>ſuch</hi> continue under the Power of ſin, willfully chooſing the way of Deſtruction, and hardning their own Hearts againſt all the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:188136:7"/>Methods of their Recovery; <hi>This</hi> in the Judgment of God, who Judgeth Righteous Judgment, is by far the more aſtoniſhing, and deplorable Object.</p>
               <p>For we never read of God's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of any Thing ſo much as of this. And how often, and in what paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Expreſſions doth he complain of the Obſtinacy, Unteachableneſs, and Wilfulneſs of the <hi>Jews,</hi> his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent People, <hi>Oh that they were wiſe! O that they would conſider! how long will you not be purged? when ſhall it once be? why will ye dye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> &amp;c. And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> introduceth Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, complaining to the like Purpoſe, <hi>Who hath believed our Report and to whom is the Arm of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1.</note> This was that which our compaſſionate Redeemer reſented even unto <hi>Tears,</hi> concerning <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the Dayes of his Fleſh, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the City and wept over it ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>O that thou hadſt known, even thou, in this thy day, the Things that belong to thy Peace,</hi> &amp;c. And in the verſe following the Text,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41.</note> 
                  <hi>O that my People had hearkened to my Voice, and walked in my Ways.</hi> This is the Subject Matter of the complaint
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:188136:8"/>of theſe Words, which is attended with a Threatning, of one of the heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Judgments that can be inflicted: <hi>My People would not hearken to my Voice, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>would none of me: So I gave them up,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> A moſt Reproaching Complaint. <hi>Secondly,</hi> A moſt Terrible Threatning. The Complaint is in the 11th verſe, <hi>My People would not hearken to my Voice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The moſt ſignificant Words are uſed to awaken Shame, and Indignation in the guilty Perſons againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for refuſing to hearken to the Voice of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Their Fault is aggravated from their near Relation to God, <hi>My People. Iſrael,</hi> the beloved Nation, my pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People, favoured above the Reſt of the World with many ſpecial advantages, <hi>They</hi> did not hearken to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From their Wilfulneſs, <hi>They would not hearken to me. They would none of me.</hi> For though the firſt Expreſſion in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> be only thus, My Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>did not</hi> hearken to me, yet the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Words, <hi>They would none of me,</hi> doth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:188136:8"/>lay the Blame upon their own Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and does ſufficiently Juſtify our Tranſlation of it.</p>
               <p>It is aggravated, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From what their not hearkening to Gods Voice did imply, and carry in it, <hi>That they would none of God; they refuſed to have</hi> God for their God. They cared not for any Relation to him, or Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, or Inſtruction from him, or Happineſs by him; <hi>They would none of me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> unto this Complaint in the 11th <hi>verſe</hi> is Subjoyned a <hi>terrible Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ver.</hi> 12th, <hi>So I gave them up to their Hearts Luſts, to walk in their own Councels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>Hebrew</hi> both Expreſſions are in the <hi>Future,</hi> that for their former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations God would do ſo, and the <hi>latter</hi> is the Conſequence of the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> The walking in their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, is the Fruit of their being given up to their own Hearts Luſts.</p>
               <p>There are two Things may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected as the Sum of both Verſes, to be diſcourſed of from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> That it is Matter of Juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint and Reproach, when a People,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:188136:9"/>or Perſon, will not hearken to the Voice of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That for ſuch wilful Perſons to be given up to their own Hearts Luſts, ſo as to be left of God to walk in their own Councels, is one of the moſt fearful Judgments that can be threatned, or inflicted in this World.</p>
               <p>Something I would ſpeak to the <hi>former</hi> though in order to the latter, which is principally deſigned. And what Subject more ſeaſonable, or more likely to be uſeful, unto thoſe who have the Voice of God repeated to them Week after Week, with ſuch Frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Variety, as you have it in this City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, That it is Matter of Juſt Complaint, and Reproach, for any People, or Perſon not to hearken to the Voice of</hi> God. And here it will be proper to ſhew, 1. What it is, not to hearken to the Voice of God 2. How this appears to be ſuch Juſt Matter of Complaint from God, and Reproach unto us, who are guilty of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What it is not to hearken to the Voice of God. By the Voice of God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:188136:9"/>here, we are to Underſtand, that of his Word; as is manifeſt from <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.23, 28. <hi>Verſes. This thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded I them, ſaying, Obey my Voice, and I will be your God. But they hearkned not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or inclined their Ear, but walked in the Councels and Imaginations of their own evil Hearts; therefore ſhalt thou ſay unto them, this is a Nation that Obeyeth not the Voice of the Lord their God.</hi> His inſtructing and informing Voice, is here meant, That which diſcovers the Nature of God, and our Duty, the wretched ſtate of our Caſe by the firſt Apoſtacy, and the Method of our Recovery to the Image and Life of God, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. It is alſo his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Voice, unto the Authority whereof, we all owe utmoſt Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection. It is that Voice of God which warns us of our Danger; invites us to Terms of Peace and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; directs us what we ought to do, that we may be ſaved, &amp;c. And have we not all the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World, to hearken to this Voice? carefully to attend to it? to conſider its Authority? to make a Judgment about its Neceſſity, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, about the Reaſonableneſs and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:188136:10"/>advantages of our Obedience? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now there be many that <hi>Openly,</hi> and <hi>Expreſly</hi> refuſe to hearken to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Voice. But the Number is greater of ſuch, who do it <hi>Vertually,</hi> and in <hi>Effect:</hi> either by their groundleſs Cavils and Objections againſt the Word of God; or by their frivolous Excuſes, and tool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Delays of complying with it; or by Obeying the contrary Dictates of the Fleſh and the World, and hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Voice of <hi>Satan;</hi> by all which they manifeſt their Unwillingneſs to hearken to the Voice of God.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> How does this appear to be ſuch a Matter of Juſt <hi>Complaint</hi> and <hi>Reproach?</hi> To this Purpoſe we may conſider, 1. <hi>Whoſe Voice it is</hi> you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> refuſe to hearken to:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.</note> the Voice of God <hi>by his Son,</hi> Whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Heir of all Things, and by whom he made the World, the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Fathers Glory, the Expreſs Image of nis Perſon.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2.</note> If Diſobedience to the Word ſpoken by Angels, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Juſt Recompence of Reward, <hi>How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect, and ſlight,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:188136:10"/>and will not hearken to that Word of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which began to be ſpoken by our Lord himſelf. See therefore (ſayes the Apoſtle) that you refuſe not him that ſpeaketh;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb</hi> 12.25. <hi>ver.</hi>
                     </note> for if they Eſcaped not who refuſed him that ſpake on Earth, Much more ſhall not we Eſcape if we turn away from him that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from Heaven.</hi> I might amplify this by Conſidering the Authority, the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity, the Wiſdom, the Kindneſs and Condeſcention, of him that ſpeaketh; and to whom we are called, and Obliged to hearken.</p>
               <p>I might aggravate it, by Conſidering how all our Senſes, and our Reaſon, our Power of Hearing, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding are all from <hi>Him:</hi> And how often he hath heard <hi>our Voice</hi> when we have cryed to him in our Diſtreſs. And how ready he is to hear us in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of need, when none elſe can help or ſave us: And how ſeverely he can puniſh our Refuſal: For in his hand is our Life and Breath, and all our Ways. It is he who hath Power to ſave or to Deſtroy and ſhall we refuſe to hearken to <hi>his Voice?</hi> Yea further, he deſignes our Good, and intends our Happineſs, by what he ſpeaks. He can
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:188136:11"/>have no Acceſſion to his own by our Felicity, but might glorify himſelf in our Ruine, if we decline the Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Mercy, and refuſe to heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to his Voice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, not only who it is that ſpeaks, but <hi>what kind of Voice it is.</hi> How gentle, how obliging, how beneficent, and condeſcending. He doth not now ſpeak to us with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Terrour, in Thunder and Lightning, with ſuch an amazing Voice as upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to the People of the <hi>Jews:</hi> When he made <hi>the Mountaine ſhake, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Tremble,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26.</note> and even Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es himſelf exceedingly to do ſo.</hi> But imploys Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers like our ſelves, to ſpeak in his Name. He conſiders our weakneſs, and the Neceſſity of our Caſe, and promiſes to accompany the ordinary Preaching of the Goſpel, with the Power of his Spirit. That the great and neceſſary truths publiſhed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and preſſed, by a ſerious Miniſtry, ſhall be the Power of God unto Salvation. He requires thoſe that are intruſted with this work, to inſtruct, to exhort, to warn and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:188136:11"/>reprove, to beſeech and intreat you in the Name of Chriſt, with Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Importunity, that you would not receive the Grace of God in vain; that you would be reconciled to God, praying you in Chriſt's ſtead that you would be ſo, leaſt the Things that concern your Peace ſhould be for Ever hid from your Eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, <hi>Who They are, that are ſaid to refuſe to hearken to the Voice of God. My People Iſrael.</hi> My Firſt born, more nearly related to me, more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly favoured and priviledged by me than the reſt of the World. We Chriſtians ſucceed in their Priviledges, not only as Domeſtick Servants, but as <hi>Children,</hi> viſibly related to God, as our Father, by the Covenant of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. And ſhall not Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren receive the Inſtruction of a Parent?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18.</note> a ſtubborn Son that refuſed to hearken to the Voice of his natural Parent, was under the Law, to be <hi>stoned to Death:</hi> and all the Men in the City, were to have a Hand in bringing ſuch a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to that deſerved Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the Complaint and Reproach is Juſt, will appear by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:188136:12"/>
                  <hi>what is Connected with</hi> it, in the Words that immediately follow, <hi>Iſrael would none of me,</hi> that is, if they will not hearken to my Voice, they declare <hi>they will have none of me.</hi> God offers himſelf to enter into a Covenant, and <hi>to be your God;</hi> only obey my Voice and I will be ſo But they inquire not after him. There is none that ſaith, <hi>where is God my Maker?</hi> They will none of me, <hi>i e</hi> they will not have me to be their Lord and Ruler, they will not have me to be their Portion and Chief Good. It is plain they will not, becauſe they refuſe my Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Guidance; they will not heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to my Voice.</p>
               <p>Now this being duely attended to, will ſufficiently Juſtify the Divine Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, v. 12. towards ſuch who will not hearken to the Voice of God. For thereby they do in Effect bid him <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part</hi> from them, they tell him, <hi>we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not the Knowledge of thy Ways.</hi> And if hereafter he ſhould bid them <hi>depart</hi> from him <hi>into Everlaſting Fire,</hi> with the Workers of Iniquity, the Sentence would not be more <hi>dreadful</hi> than <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> If he ſay, Depart from me, you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:188136:12"/>unthankful deſpiſers of my Grace; I would have inſtructed, and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaved you, <hi>but you would not;</hi> I called, but you refuſed, and turned the deaf Ear; I exhorted, and beſeeched, and intreated you to have Pity on your ſelves in Time, but you would not hearken to my Voice. I faithfully warned you of your danger, but you made light of it. I offered to be <hi>your God,</hi> and to make you happy and bleſſed for Ever, if you would but <hi>accept</hi> my offer; but <hi>you would none of me.</hi> Therefore if he ſhould ſpeak to them hereafter in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore Diſpleaſure: if he <hi>then</hi> be Deaf to their Crys, who <hi>now</hi> refuſe to hearken to his Voice, their Sentence will be Juſt.</p>
               <p>And no leſs would it be if God ſhould inflict the heavy Doom mentioned in this Text: which is the Beginning of Hell, where it continues without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and timely Relief is not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Such as will not hearken to the Voice of God; the Language of whoſe Heart is thereby manifeſt, that they will none of him, Such as theſe, God may Juſtly <hi>give up to their own Hearts Luſts; and leave them to walk in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:188136:13"/>their own deſtructive Councels.</hi> And this brings me to conſider <hi>the Second Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That for wilful Sinners to be given up to their own Hearts Luſts, and to be left of God to walk in their own Councels, is one of the moſt tremendous Judgments that can be threatned, or inflicted in this World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is it for God to give up any to their own Hearts Luſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is his uſual Method of inflicting ſuch a Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Wherein does the Terrour and Dread of ſuch a Judgment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? or what Conſiderations will manifeſt this to be ſuch a diſmal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? What I ſhall ſpeak under theſe <hi>Three Heads</hi> will make way for the practical Application.</p>
               <p>I muſt grant that there is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Depth in the divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; eſpecially in his Methods of Severity towards the Souls of Men: And therefore when we have gone as far as Scripture and Experience will direct and lead us, we muſt yet cry out, <hi>O the bottomleſs Depths of the Divine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:188136:13"/>Councels: how unſearchable are his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33: <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4.</note> and his ways paſt finding out?</hi> However, we muſt hold to this, that <hi>all his Works are perfect:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that <hi>he is a God of Truth, and without Iniquity; his Ways are Judgment,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.3, 4.</note> and Juſt and Right is he.</hi> And it is remarkable that this is ſpoken after a terrible Expreſſion a little before concerning the <hi>Jews,</hi> that after having ſeen the Signs and Wonders and Miracles that God wrought among them, <hi>yet hath he not given you a Heart to perceive, and Eyes to ſee, and Ears to hear, unto this Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whatever Obſcurity there may be in the Manner, yet ſuch a Thing as Gods leaving Men to themſelves muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; yea,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.12.</note> his pouring out a ſpirit of ſlumber and deep ſleep upon Men, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Eyes in righteous Judgment, after they have wilfully ſhut them.</p>
               <p>Never was any People ſo puniſhed in this Manner, as the Nation of the <hi>Jews.</hi> After having long reſiſted the Spirit, neither Word, nor Rod could awaken them, but the Things of their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:188136:14"/>Peace, were hid from their Eyes. But we muſt not conceive of this, as an Act merely of <hi>Will and Pleaſure</hi> in God; without Reſpect to their former ſin. But conſider it <hi>as an act of Righteous Judgment, upon great Provocation.</hi> This Doom never goes before the Fault; when they will not be purged, they are left to be filthy ſtill. After long ſtriving and Reſiſtance God lets 'em Alone. We muſt view it as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>Judicial</hi> toward thoſe who had highly deſerved it, by former Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of his Grace, and diſobeying his Voice: And therefore when God is ſaid in the 4th of <hi>Exodus</hi> to harden <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> let us conſider who he was, and what he had done: Was he not guilty of the moſt prophane contempt of God, <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his Voice? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Iſrael go, Exod.</hi> 5.2. And was he not guilty of the moſt barbarous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and Cruelty againſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God? Had he not for many years oppreſt, and inſlaved them? were not He and his Subjects reſolved to deſtroy thoſe whom God reſolved to preſerve? &amp;c. He is <hi>three times</hi> ſaid to have hardned his own heart.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:188136:14"/>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.15, 32. And <hi>chap.</hi> 9.34. Tho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had ſufficient means of Conviction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod ſwallowing up thoſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Magicians,</hi> 7 <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.2. And by the <hi>Magicians</hi> being non-pluſt in their Art; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oncerning the Judgment of Lice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18. And they themſelves were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitten with Boils, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.11, 12. And now and then <hi>Pharoah</hi> had ſome Relentings, <hi>chap.</hi> 9.27, 10. <hi>chap.</hi> 16.17.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Jews</hi> in our Saviour's Time, concerning whom the like Expreſſions are uſed, <hi>John</hi> 12.40. They were ſuch as hated the Light, as would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his Forerunner the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> but ſaid of both, that they were poſſeſſed of a Devil. In this Caſe we may uſe the Apoſtles Expreſſion, <hi>Is God unrighteous, who taketh Vengeance?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.5.</note> God forbid.</hi> Here indeed is very diſmal Severity, but there is no ſhadow of unrighteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>This being premiſed, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>First,</hi> What theſe Luſts of Mens Hearts are? <hi>Secondly,</hi> What it is to be given up <hi>Judicially</hi> to them.</p>
               <p>The Luſts of our Hearts unto which ſome are given up by God, may Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the falſe Imaginations, and undue Conceptions of Things that are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:188136:15"/>framed in the Soul, concerning God, and our ſelves, Sin and Duty, Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Miſery, &amp;c. And our Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Deſires, and Inclinations; with all the wicked Projects, and Contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of the Soul, concerning the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and fulfilling the Luſts of the Fleſh, the Luſts of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life.</p>
               <p>Now for God to give up any Men to theſe Luſts, ſo as not to hinder them from walking in their own Councels, is not to be ſuppoſed as if he gave his <hi>approving Conſent,</hi> that they ſhould obey theſe Luſts: Not that he gave them leave to ſin, or approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what they did, in ſerving divers Luſts, but that which is chiefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in it is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſuch Perſons are caſt out of Gods ſpecial Protection and Care, and ſo are expoſed to wander and go aſtray:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>To walk as a Lamb in alarge Place,</hi> and ſo are more eaſily aſſaulted, and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the Devil, who ſeeketh whom he may deſtroy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That they are left of God under the Dominion, and Power, and Tyranny of their own Luſts; <hi>He that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:188136:15"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> filthy let him be filthy ſtill.</hi> Rom. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>He that heareth let him hear; and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at forbeareth let him forbear, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey are a Rebellious Houſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.27.</note> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the Reſtraints and Checks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they were formerly under, by the Motions of his Spirit; or by External Providence, ſhould no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onger hinder them in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of their Luſts.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.34. <hi>Eze.</hi> 24, 13.16, 4. <hi>Hoſ</hi> 4.14.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall not be ſmitten any more,</hi> nor their way hedged up with Thorns. The Spirit of God ſhall not ſtrive with them any more; at leaſt not to ſuch a Degree as formerly.</p>
               <p>Nay further, we read of Mens being given up, after ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Light, unto a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28, 29, 30, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Reprobate unteachable Mind, to vile affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ons, to unnatural Luſts.</hi> Yea, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to
<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrong Deluſions of Satan,</hi> that they may believe Lyes, that they may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But remember this is an Act of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in God; for the Perſons thus given up are deſcrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to be ſuch <hi>as would not receive the Truth in the Love of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is ſuch a Judgment as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:188136:16"/>this, beſides the Expreſs Teſtimoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Scripture, is manifeſt by <hi>ſad Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> For what tolerable account can be otherwiſe given of the Generality of profeſſing Chriſtians, with whom the ſence of Duty, the Honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, the Intereſt of his Kingdom have ſo little Influence, to a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious governing their Hearts an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lives? Yea how elſe is it? That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Mercies and Judgments notwithſtanding providential warning and gracious Calls, notwithſtanding many Convictions and Reſolutions and good Beginnings, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many ſevere Rebukes for paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Backſlidings, and ſome Experience how evil and bitter a Thing it is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and hath been, to forſake God that yet in Deſpite of God, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and all theſe Obſtacles in their way, many have forſaken the Way of Righteouſneſs, and wallowed againe in the Pollutions of the World, after they had eſcaped it. And whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Hazard they run by it, whatever Difficulties they meet in their way, whatever Methods have been uſed to recover and ſave them, yet on they will go: and from a ſeeming Zeal for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:188136:16"/>God and Godlineſs, and conſtant day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Exerciſe of the principal Duties of Religion in their Families, and Cloſets, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey come at laſt to live without any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f theſe; in the total Neglect of ſuch Duties, and in allowed Practiſes of Drunkeneſs, Uncleaneſs, and Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, with the Contempt of the Means of their Converſion, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Enmity againſt the true Intereſt of Chriſt in the World, and againſt the ſerious Profeſſion and Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Friends,</hi> The Caſe of ſuch Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and the more common Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of many Others, after good and hopeful Beginnings, who have ſinned themſelves into a quiet peaceful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or rather into ſtupidity and Hardneſs of Heart, notwithſtanding the Dayly Commiſſion of great Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; the deplorable Caſe, I ſay, of ſuch Perſons, and the Frequency of ſuch Caſes, makes it manifeſt that there is ſuch a Thing as mens being left of God, and given up to their own Hearts Luſts.</p>
               <p>But remember, I call it a <hi>deplorable Caſe,</hi> not an <hi>irrecoverable</hi> one. For I do not think, as to all ſuch Perſons, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:188136:17"/>their Day of Grace is paſt; that the Things of their Peace are ſo hid from their Eyes, that it is impoſſible for them to be renewed to Repentance. There are Degrees of Gods forſaking Men; there is a <hi>total</hi> and there is a <hi>partial Obduracy</hi> and Hardneſs of Heart But I ſhall ſpeak more of this afterwards.</p>
               <p>We ſhould <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider by <hi>what Method</hi> God does for the moſt part proceed, to inflict and Execute ſuch a Judgment as this. But</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> For the preſent let us briefly conſider the <hi>Severity</hi> and <hi>Terrour</hi> of this Judgment. According to the Degrees of this Puniſhment inflicted on any, ſo is the Wretchedneſs of their Caſe in Proportion to be eſtimated. For a Man to be totally left to the Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Obduracy of his own Heart, there is no Judgment in this World ſo ſevere: and therefore ſayes
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Owens Dominion of Sin, Page</hi> 73.</note> Dr. <hi>Owen, it is never Executed, but towards thoſe that are habitually and obſtinately wicked, and do out of choice harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may Conſider the Dread and Horrour of ſuch a Judgment by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:188136:17"/>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, &amp;c. Very much may be gathered from <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. Where we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt ſignificant Repreſentation of ſuch a diſmal Caſe, in our Lords affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Bewailing of the Miſery of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as forſaken and left of God. <hi>He beheld the City,</hi> and mingled his Lamentations over it with his <hi>Tears.</hi> Saying, <hi>O! Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, if thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt, in this thy Day, the Things which belong unto thy Peace! but now they are hid from thine Eyes.</hi> He knew how deplorable the Condition of ſuch Perſons muſt needs be, and what was due to ſo great a Calamity, or he would not have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented it with Tears. He knew the aggravation of their Guilt, and the Severity of the Divine Juſtice, and the Value of Immortal Souls, and the Depth of Miſery, into which ſuch guilty ſinners are ſinking; he perfectly knew theſe Things, or he would not have beſtowed Tears upon this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
               <p>And which yet is moſt
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See Mr.</hi> How's <hi>Redeemers Tears. Pag.</hi> 149.</note> Dreadful to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:188136:18"/>conſider, when Perſons are becom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> incurably Obſtinate, and Impeniten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto Perdition, the Redeemers Tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may Expreſs his Compaſſion, but wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not abate their Miſery, or aſſwag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Torment. They that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and diſpiſed his Mercy, and trampled upon his Blood, ſhall ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have his Tears of Compaſſion. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> former would have ſaved them, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the latter only bewails their Folly, and their Miſery, what they have loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe they would not be ſaved. They neglected God's ſeaſon and he departed, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.6. <hi>They ſhall go with their flocks and with their herds to ſeek the Lord: But they ſhall not find him: He hath withdrawn himſelf from them. So John</hi> 8.21. <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaid Jeſus again unto them, I go my way, and ye ſhall ſeek me, and ſhall dy in your ſins: Whither I go, ye cannot come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for me to deſcribe the Horrour of their Caſe, with whom Matters are come to this Iſſue: That God reſolves <hi>to let them alone,</hi> to give them up into the Hands of their own Counſels, to leave them to their own Hearts Luſts, to the Dominion and Tyranny of their vile Affections
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:188136:18"/>and Inclinations, <hi>that they ſhall be holden in the Cords of their own Iniquity, and without further Inſtruction, or Reſtraint,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.22, 23.</note> in the midst of their Folly, be left of God to go aſtray.</hi> When becauſe they would not be purged, they ſhall not be purged, till the Divine Fury be made to reſt upon them. God will <hi>let them Alone,</hi> and ſay, if they will go on to treaſure up Wrath againſt a Day of Wrath, <hi>e'ne let them do it;</hi> If they will harden their Hearts, if they will dye, if they are ſo intent upon their own Ruin, as that they refuſe my counſel, and ſlight my Reproofs, and reſiſt my Spirit, and hate to be Reform'd; let them take their Courſe, let them walk in the Ways of their own Heart, and in the Sight of their Eyes, let them proſecute their own fooliſh Choice; I will do nothing to hinder it: My Goſpel ſhall not inſtruct and heal them; My Spirit ſhall not to any good purpoſe longer ſtrive with them; that which is the Savour of Life, and the Power of God unto ſalvation unto Others, ſhall have a deadly Savour unto them.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:188136:19"/>
               <p>No words can expreſs <hi>the Horrour of</hi> ſuch a Caſe. And ſuch a Caſe is <hi>poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> but we have no certaine Rule giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us whereby to determine our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning any particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo as to enable us to ſay poſitively, <hi>This is the ſad condition of ſuch a Man, or ſuch a Woman:</hi> But becauſe many fear it is their own Caſe, and the Perſon, who by a Letter deſired me to preach on this Subject, is afraid leſt Things may already be come to this Iſſue, I will not now cloſe without ſome <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Paſſing over ſeveral Uſes that may be made of this, I ſhall hence take Occaſion to Exhort to three Things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To take heed not to paſs a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive Sentence againſt your ſelves, concerning the ſtate of your own Souls, as to this Judgment. <hi>Secondly,</hi> However to apprehend the Danger of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, if you are under any ill Symptoms of that kind, and beware of thoſe Things that have a Tendency to ſo ſad a Doom <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Diligently to improve the Means you are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by the Warnings of the Word,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:188136:19"/>convictions of Conſcience, and the Motions of the Divine Spirit, that you may Effectually prevent it. That as it is not your Caſe for the preſent, it never may be ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Take heed of paſſing a defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Sentence againſt your ſelves in this matter. There is a Time even with the Impenitent and Unconverted, when God may move their Hearts more ſtrongly unto Converſion, than after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And when ſuch a Time is over with thee, thou mayeſt be apt to think that God hath utterly Abandon'd, and Forſaken thee; and be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <hi>Thy Day of Grace is paſt.</hi> In this Senſe it may be paſt with many long before their Death, and yet their ſtate not be irrecoverable. This is like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be the Caſe of many of you preſent; but you need not thereupon queſtion but you ſhall be accepted of God, if you are <hi>now</hi> willing to return to him. You have no ground to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether Chriſt will receive you, if you are willing to come to him; or whether pardoning Mercy may be had if you penitently forſake your wicked ways, and turn to the Lord with all your heart.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:188136:20"/>
               <p>Men that formerly had ſome Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Helps to Repentance, which they neglected and miſimproved, and obſtinately reſiſted, may be ſo given up to their Obſtinacy, as never to have ſuch Motions more; and ſo on that Account <hi>the Day of Grace</hi> may be paſt with divers. But ſuch Perſons are hardened in Sin, and hate an Holy Life, oppoſe ſerious Godlineſs, and the Means of their Recovery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>the Day of Grace</hi> is never ſo paſt in this Life with any Man, as that he ſhall not be accepted and pardoned, if he do truly repent. Therefore for a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent returning Sinner to fear his Day of Grace is utterly paſt, or that his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, if it be true, does now come too late; This is to contradict the whole Tenour and Scope of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. Your Caſe may be more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than that of moſt others, and yet not <hi>Irrecoverable.</hi> Be ſure it is not, if you have not ſinn'd that Sin which can't be pardon'd; which in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, I firmly believe no man is guilty of, who is afraid leſt he hath been, or is ſo guilty.</p>
               <p>Our Obſtinate continued forſaking of God, is the great ſign of our being
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:188136:20"/>forſaken of him: And where that is not the Caſe, you ſhould not Judg ſo concerning your ſelves, or others. And even where it is ſo, for the preſent, the Grace of God may be rejected for many years; and yet we may hope that ſome Perſons may afterwards be converted by that Grace, which before they rejected. So that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what God will do as to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons. Neither would it be any advantage for us to know if ſuch and ſuch, be ſo far forſaken of God, as that they ſhall never be recovered, but continue in their Obſtinacy and Impentiency to the End of their Days. God hath
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> How's <hi>Redeemers Tears, pag.</hi> 82.</note> not made it any Man's Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to believe this concerning himſelf, nor to beleive it concerning any other particular Perſon.</p>
               <p>Some of thoſe whoſe Hearts were once as hard as yours, who ſlighted Chriſt as much, and as long, as you have done, who diſpiſed many awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening Warnings, who refuſed and turn'd their Backs upon many Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Calls of the Goſpel, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the Spirit of Grace for a long
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:188136:21"/>Time, have afterwards been made the Triumph of the Power, Love and Grace of God. Therefore don't paſs a definitive Sentence againſt your ſelves.</p>
               <p>To paſs a Judgment upon our State, and to believe it concerning our ſelves, is to nullity the Goſpel, and to make it impoſſible for us to Repent and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, which God hath made to be our Duty. It is a ſinful preſcribing limits to the Grace of God, to ſay, <hi>It hath waited on me ſo long, it will, it can wait no longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> However Apprehend the Danger of the preſent Caſe, if you are under any ſuch Symptoms as have a Tendency to ſo ſevere a Judgment as this is. It may be you have ſinned your ſelves into hardneſs of Heart; that you are not affected with the Word Preached as formerly; that you do not find ſuch Impreſſions by it; that the Operations of the Spirit, with the Word, that were formerly ſtrong, do now ſeem to ceaſe. You are not ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Evil of Sin, with ſuch hearty Sorrow, and bitter Repentance as formerly, tho thy ſins be moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aggravated; And are little affected with the ſins of others; you are more
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:188136:21"/>ſenceleſs, ſtupid, and ſecure under the Guilt of great Provocations, than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: And this, notwithſtanding ſome Tokens of God's Diſpleaſure by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictive Rebukes of Providence. It may be you have taken up with a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, barren, empty Profeſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for a long Time; joyn'd with the Neglect of the inward Spiritual Part of Godlineſs, Mortification of Sin, Watchfulneſs over your Hearts, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of your Thoughts, Paſſions, and Sences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And have gone on in a formal Courſe and Round, of ſome external Duties; without Heart, or Life, or Quickning; and this contrary to your Convictions, Reſolutions, and repeated Promiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This caſe is exceeding ſad, and ſinful, and <hi>God</hi> only knows where it will Iſſue, if deep and timely Repentance do not awaken you. You ought to apprehend it to be indeed a very <hi>provoking,</hi> and <hi>dangerous Caſe,</hi> but not quite <hi>deſperate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, let me go further, <hi>Secret Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> it may be, hath been neglected for a Time, or performed with ſo much coldneſs, that <hi>you now Tremble</hi> to think how low you are ſunk: Or which is much worſe, it may be you do <hi>not</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:188136:22"/>Tremble. The Power of Conſcience is in a great meaſure loſt, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining from Sin, and in checking for it. You can now more eaſily ſtifle Convictions, rebel againſt Light, and venture upon a known ſin, indulge a ſecret Luſt, and allow your ſelves thoſe Things from day to day, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you could not without ſharp Rebukes of Conſcience: And ſuch Preaching, and ſuch Helps as did once ſtartle, awaken, and quicken you, have now little or no ſuch Effect; This is indeed unſpeakably diſmal. O! how low are ſuch fallen? how difficult, how ſorrowful muſt be the awakening and Recovery of ſuch Backſliders? What can be ſaid to ſuch Perſons? and why ſhould they not fear the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Text? leſt <hi>God give them up to their own Hearts Luſts.</hi> I am ſo far from diſcouraging <hi>ſuch a Fear,</hi> that I would by all Means awaken it. Therefore I ſay it would be <hi>Juſt</hi> with God, to caſt thee off, and God would be Righteous, if he reject thee utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he forſake thee for Ever, if he never ſtrive with thy Heart more, if Never Providence or Sermon do thee good more. This would be <hi>Juſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:188136:22"/>But at the ſame Time let <hi>Hope</hi> be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled with <hi>Fear;</hi> there is much Cauſe to <hi>Fear,</hi> but there is none to <hi>Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair,</hi> the one is a <hi>Duty,</hi> and the other <hi>a Sin:</hi> And if the Conſideration of your ſin and Danger, begin to melt and mollify your Heart, then know that Chriſt came not to call the Righteous, but <hi>Sinners,</hi> to Repentance; and mercy may yet be had; <hi>he takes pleaſure in them that hope in his Mercy; it is by hope we are ſaved.</hi> Therefore aggravate your ſins, and the grounds of your Fear, and the Danger of your periſhing to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: But don't ſit down in Deſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; don't yeild your ſelves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, without ſtriving to prevent it. Fall down before his Mercy-Seat, ſtudy the Nature, and Promiſes of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and fly to Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the general Invitation, and Call of the Goſpel to that End.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if your Hearts begin to melt, and move within you, who have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended your ſelves in Danger of this Judgment, if you are yet under the ſtrivings of the Spirit, (as your very Sollicitude and Fear about it, and Deſire of Aſſiſtance, doth Imply,) then I would beſeech you to ſet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:188136:23"/>to work out your Salvation with all Diligence. Let not the Dictates of an awakened Conſcience be huſh'd, and ſilenc'd: Cheriſh and obey the holy Motions of the Spirit: Let not your preſent Convictions and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions become abortive, for want of Meditation, and Prayer, and adviſing with your Miniſters, and Judicious, Faithful Friends. Eſpecially take heed of extinguiſhing the Sentiments of an awakened Conſcience by new Guilt, and freſh Tranſgreſſions. While Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is thus at Work, your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is more probable, and hopeful now than formerly: If you quench not the Motions of the Spirit, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to leave you. If you will but hearken to his Voice and follow his Counſel, and not again harden your Hearts: If you would <hi>now</hi> earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implore, and thankfully entertaine, and carefully improve his holy Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
               <p>Is it not of higheſt Importance, that you do ſo without Delay? When your Breath is in your Noſtrils, <hi>and the Day of your Life, and your Day of Grace, may both be ended before to morrow Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Should not the Kindneſs of God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:188136:23"/>overcome you? That Mercy is offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſuch returning Backſliders? ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not be a melting, tranſporting Thought, for ſuch <hi>as you</hi> to conſider, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Chriſt invites you to come to him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you are weary and heavy laden, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>romiſes Reſt. Read <hi>Judges,</hi> 10th the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atter End, for your Encouragment, where God having delivered his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they yet forſook him, it is ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat <hi>he would deliver them no more,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id them go to the Gods they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſen: But they cryed to him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urned from their evil Ways, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oul was greived for them, and <hi>he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eliver them.</hi> They cryed heartily, <hi>Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o unto us what ſeemeth thee good, only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver us,</hi> ſo do you in like Manner, and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here is yet Hope;</hi> Go in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecret, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell him, that it is the Deſire of your Souls, now to return to him, beg his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anctifying Spirit with utmoſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unity, plead the Vertue of the Blood of Chriſt, ſay unto him, <hi>Lord do with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne what thou wilt;</hi> afflict me how thou pleaſeſt, ſtrip me of all my pleaſant Things, if that may ſerve the Ends of <hi>thy Glory;</hi> only let not thy holy Spirit forſake me; only deliver me out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hands of my Luſts; break theſe my
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:188136:24"/>Chains, knock off theſe Fetters; ſave me from my ſins, and from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wrath; accept me for thy Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervant, write thy Law upon my Heart, that I may walk in thy Ways. And whatever thou give me, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou deny me, <hi>Lord, for Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt's ſake, never give me up to my ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hearts Lusts, that I ſhould be left to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in my own Counſels.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:188136:24"/>
               <head>The Second Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſalm LXXXI. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>I gave them up to their own Hearts luſts: and they walked in their own Counſels.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WE can never look back to our primitive ſtate, conſidering how richly and plentifully the Bounty of our Maker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad provided for us, without admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Thoughts of his Beneficence and Kindneſs: And yet, if we view the Divine Compaſſion unto guilty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebellious Man ſince the Fall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow many obſtacles his Grace over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame; This latter will be Judged to ſurpaſs his former Bounty to Innocent
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:188136:25"/>Man. For before the Entrance of ſin, the Current of Divine Love met with nothing to obſtruct its paſſage, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was nothing to diſcourage its Exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe towards an Innocent and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Creature: But now ſin hath made a great gulf betwixt God and us; We are in a ſtate of Enmity, and Hoſtility againſt Him; which ſets a value upon the Power, and Freeneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Grace imployed to Recove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſave us.</p>
               <p>And yet, after all this diſplay of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unſearchable Riches of Grace, and Love in the Work of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is a queſtion whether our will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, provoking Obſtinacy againſt God be not more aſtoniſhing, than his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved Compaſſion and Love to us that in contradiction to all the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Reaſon, and Intereſt, we ſhould ſlight his Kindneſs, and deſpiſe his glorious Love, and refuſe his Grace, the only Remedy that can ſave us. That when he offers to be Reconciled to us, and Intreats us to be Reconcile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to him, we will not hearken to his Voice: That we ſhould perſiſt in our choſen Diſtance, and Eſtrangment, and ſay, <hi>We will have none of him;</hi> Let
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:188136:25"/>him depart from us, we deſire not the Knowledge of his ways; We care for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Reconciliation to him, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, or any ſhare in the Happineſs he offers to confer upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Were not this very highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oking, the Bleſſed God would not <hi>Complain</hi> of it, as he doth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Repreach</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with it, as he alſo doth, in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laces, and particularly in this, <hi>My People would not hearken to my Voice, and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſrael <hi>would none of me; ſo I gave them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p, &amp;c.</hi> Both Expreſſions are in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uture,</hi> though we tranſlate them as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady inflicted: The Original ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es that God <hi>would</hi> deal ſo ſeverely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith them. The Aggravations of his Complaint of God concerning <hi>Iſrael</hi> have been already mentioned. What I propoſe now to diſcourſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it is matter of moſt Juſt Complaint, and moſt heavy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roach, when any People or Perſon will not hearken to the Voice of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That for any wilful ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers to be given up by God to their own Hearts Luſts, and left to walk in their own Counſels, is one of the moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:188136:26"/>Judgments that can be threatned, or inflicted.</p>
               <p>In ſpeaking to the <hi>Second</hi> General, I propoſed to ſhew, <hi>Firſt,</hi> What it is fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God to give Men up to their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hearts Luſts. And that ſuch a thing there <hi>may be,</hi> and <hi>is,</hi> as Gods giving men over to their falſe Imaginations and Conceptions of things; their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Deſires and irregular Paſſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their wicked Projects and Contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances for the fulfilling of their variou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Luſts, &amp;c. When he gives them up to theſe Luſts, he caſts them out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpecial Care and Protection, ſo as they become an eaſy prey to the Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And the Hebrew word which we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate <hi>give up,</hi> is often uſed for <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> caſting out</hi> a People out of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as in 44. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. Such Perſons a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo left of God under the Tyranny and Dominion of their Luſts, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe Reſtraints of Providence an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grace which before they had. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more may be intended in ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, will appear in ſpeaking to <hi>the Second Head,</hi> viz.</p>
               <p>To ſhew <hi>by what steps and Degrees, God doth execute, and inflict ſuch a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them.</hi> And then, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:188136:26"/>ſhall ſpeak ſomething further of the <hi>Dreadfulneſs</hi> of this Judgment, and ſo <hi>Apply</hi> the whole.</p>
               <p n="2">II. By What ſteps or Degrees the Bleſſed God doth uſually proceed in inflicting ſuch a Judgment as this. For the better underſtanding of this, I muſt premiſe by way of Caution.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Whatever Method is taken in the Execution of ſo ſevere a Doom, we muſt remember there is a great depth of <hi>Obſcurity</hi> in theſe Judgments of God; There is ſo in all his works of Judgment, but eſpecially in ſuch as do more immediately relate to the Souls of Men. We know very little of the manner of Gods Influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens Spirits, and therefore ſhould be very humble and wary, modeſt and cautions in our Expreſſions about it. And yet from what we obſerve of ſuch ſpiritual Judgments, we may cry out with the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33 <hi>O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledg of God! How unſearchable are his Judgments, and his Ways paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out!</hi> We know very little of the manner of the Holy Spirit's Influence, in forming the Image of God upon the Soul; and much leſs concerning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:188136:27"/>the manner of this Puniſhment in the Text; whereby men are hardened in ſin through the righteous Judgment of God, to their Eternal Ruine. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Remember, This is <hi>a Judicial Act</hi> in God, not an arbitrary thing, that depends upon meer Will and Pleaſure, without any reſpect to the Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mens wilful Rebellion, and ſinning againſt Light. It is ſuch a Judgment as ſuppoſes very hainous Provocations to precede it. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Jews</hi> doth abundantly prove this; with whom the Patience of God did long bear, and his Spirit ſtrive; But <hi>they alwaies reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt, Acts</hi> 7.51. From generation to generation, maintaining the war againſt the Divine Spirit, <hi>till he turned to be their Enemy, and fought againſt them. Iſa.</hi> 63.9, 10. And then their Doom is pronounc'd in a moſt ſolemn manner, with terrible and aſtoniſhing Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. By a glorious Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of the great God in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which made the Prophet cry out, <hi>I am undone,</hi> &amp;c. The fearful meſſage he was to deliver, to that People, was that 9, 10. <hi>v. Hear ye indeed, but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:188136:27"/>not; ſee ye indeed, but perceive not; make the Heart of this people fat, and their ears heavy, and ſhut their Eyes, leſt they ſee with their Eyes, and hear with their Ears, and underſtand with their Heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and be healed.</hi> This Doom we find with great Awfulneſs repeated in the new Teſtament by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.10.12. <hi>John</hi> 40. And afterward by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> when he was teſtifying againſt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Infidelity of the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Rome, Rom.</hi> 11.8. We may therefore clear <hi>the Righteouſneſs</hi> of God in this matter, by conſidering the true Account and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of Thoſe, whom we find in Scripture, or believe by Experience, to have been given up to their own Hearts Luſts. The Wickedneſs of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> was riſen to a very provoking height, before God is ſaid to harden him, which was not till after the <hi>ſixth</hi> Plague. The impenitent <hi>Cananites</hi> had 430 Years, before God gave them over, and their meaſure was full, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 11.19. <hi>This</hi> therefore, as it is one of <hi>the ſevereſt Judgments,</hi> ſo it is one of <hi>the laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This alſo may admit of <hi>Degrees</hi> with reference to ſeveral Perſons. For
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:188136:28"/>there is a <hi>partial,</hi> as well as a <hi>total</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking of God, and being forſaken of him. There are ſome who ſin againſt their Light, and refuſe the Grace of the Goſpel, and may <hi>for a time</hi> be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and left of God, and yet his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>afterwards</hi> ſtrive again; Whereas with others he may <hi>never</hi> ſtrive more. However in all theſe Caſes there is great Provocation that does precede, ſo that we may ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Is God unrighteous, that he taketh Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence? Rom.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I would alſo premiſe, That <hi>the Holineſs</hi> of God muſt be cleared, as well as his <hi>Justice.</hi> Though he give them up to their own Hearts Luſts, it is not by a conſenting, approving Act, with reference to the ſins they afterwards commit; much leſs that God inclines their Hearts to ſin, or infuſes, or ſuggeſts evil to them. It is not that He gives them Indulgence and Leave, with his Conſent and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, to ſerve and fulfil any of thoſe Luſts. The ſpotleſs unchanga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Purity of the Divine Nature, which hates every ſin, cannot conſiſt with this. <hi>He cannot be tempted with Evil, neither tempteth any man to evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:188136:28"/>
               <p>Therefore ſuch Expreſſions as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.39. <hi>As for you, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord, go you now every one and ſerve his Idols.</hi> Such Expreſſions muſt be taken in an <hi>Ironical</hi> ſenſe. That is, <q>Go ſee whether the Objects of your Truſt, and Confidence can ſave you in a time of Calamity: Go to the Gods that you have ſerved, and ſee whether they will help you, for I will not.</q> It is like the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.46. <hi>Sleep on now, and take your Rest, for behold he cometh, by whom the Son of man is to be betrayed.</hi> I deſired you to watch with me, but you would not; and that ſeaſon is now paſt, Sleep on now, if you can. When <hi>Satan</hi> blinds the Minds of men, he doth it by ſtrengthening of their ſin, he doth it by ſinful ſuggeſtions, and the like: But the Bleſſed God doth not <hi>thus</hi> give men up to ſin: No ſuch Darkneſs can come from the Fountain of Light.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being <hi>premiſed,</hi> let us Conſider ſome of thoſe ſteps, by which God preceeds in this matter, as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, and Experience may direct us; Though after all, there is <hi>a Depth</hi> in theſe Judgments of God,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:188136:29"/>which none are able fully to Explain.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When God forbears to Afflict, and to reſtrain men from ſin, by the Rod of Correction, and the Rebukes of his Providence: Or doth not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſuch Rebukes for their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We little think whither we ſhould wander, if God did <hi>not hedg up our ways with Thorns, Hoſ.</hi> 2.6, 7. If he did not by his Providence make a Wall that we ſhould not be able to find our ſinful Paths; that we ſhould not be able to make Proviſion for our Luſts at an eaſy rate, or have ſo much fewel for them as we deſire. My People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſays God by the Prophet, was reſolved to go after her Lovers; but God ſays I will make her return back in confuſion. She ſhall find an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable hedge of Thorns in her way; I will ſtop her Courſe, I will make <hi>a Wall, and a Wall,</hi> as in the Original, and ſhe ſhall not find her Paths. <hi>Tho ſhe follow after her Lovers, ſhe ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them, ſhe ſhall ſeek them but ſhall not find them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like Expreſſion you have 3. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 7, 9. <hi>He hath hedged me about that I cannot get out, he hath incloſed me with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewen ſtone.</hi> Some by the Fetters of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:188136:29"/>Education, as they call it, and are glad when they can ſhake them off; Some by the want of Money, or Intereſt, or Power, to accompliſh their wicked Purpoſes, have their Way hedged up. Sometimes by bodily Pains, and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God <hi>opens the Ears of men, and ſeals Inſtruction to them, that he may withdraw Man from his Purpoſe, and hide Pride from Man, Job</hi> 33.17, 18. God is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in very merciful to many. Young Perſons eſpecially ſhould conſider it, to whom it is a Kindneſs to have <hi>ſin</hi> made <hi>difficult</hi> to them: For if they had <hi>ſo much Liberty</hi> as they would deſire, and <hi>ſo much Money</hi> at command as they could wiſh, and were let alone by their Superiours to do as they pleaſe, and live as they liſt, without any check, or fear of loſing the favour of thoſe on whom they depend, or from whom they have their Expectation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If things were thus with them, they know not unto what Exceſs and Height of ſin they ſhould run. So for Health, and Bodily ſtrength, the abating of theſe may be a merciful Reſtraint from ſome ſort of ſins. The very weakneſs of our Conſtitutions, may be a means to ſave us from ſome kind of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:188136:30"/>which others in vigorous Health do ſtruggle with, and are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by. So for diſappointments in the World, Diſcountenance and Diſgrace, and other ſuch things, that are apt to humble and afflict the Mind. The more of <hi>theſe Reſtraints</hi> God is pleaſed to take from us, it may ſo fall out, that <hi>the more Angry</hi> he therein appeares to be. Eſpecially if former afflictive Rebukes of Providence, have been miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improved: There being hardly a more terrible place in the whole Bible, than that threatening of God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>Your Daughters ſhall commit Whoredom, and your Spouſes ſhall commit Adultery; And I will not puniſh your Daughters when they commit Whoredom, nor your Spouſes when they commit Adultery. O quanta Paena, nulla Paena!</hi> It is the greateſt Judgment, or the fore runner of that which is ſo, when God abſtains from puniſhing, when by timely Chaſtiſement he does not awaken to Repentance, and ſtop ſinners in their career; when the way to Hell is plain, and eaſy to them; when there is no Thorn, no Obſtacle in the way, but they may ſmoothly go on, and walk after their own Counſels, in the Paths
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:188136:30"/>that lead to the Chambers of Death.</p>
               <p>How many <hi>Young Perſons</hi> hath God been kind to, by thoſe Reſtraints of Providence, which he takes off from others? How hath he hedged and walled up your Way? He hath made it more difficult for you to ſin: you cannot do as others, without ſuffering more than they; either in your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or your temporal Intereſt, or your Health, &amp;c. And yet we find, notwithſtanding all this, many ſuch will not be divorced from their belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Luſts. As one of the Antients ſpeaks concerning <hi>Philotimus,</hi> who had weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened his Conſtitution, and impaired his Health, as the Effect of his Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Riot: And being told by the Phyſicians, that if he would not forbear, and preſently break off his licentious Courſe, that he muſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe his <hi>Eye ſight:</hi> There was no help for him, but in a little time he would be Blind: He preſently anſwers the Phyſician thus, <hi>Valeat lumen amicum,</hi> Farewell, O pleaſant and deſirable Light, rather than not ſin on, as I have done, I am content never to behold the Light of the Sun more. Will the Bleſſed God, think you, be <hi>unrighteous,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:188136:31"/>if he condemn ſuch reſolved ſinners to everlaſting Darkneſs? Or to give them up now to thoſe Luſts, that they are ſo madly ſet upon?</p>
               <p>But where he hath Deſigns of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to any, he will not leave them to go on without Correction. <hi>As many as I love, I rebuke and chaſten.</hi> If you will not be reclaimed by <hi>one Rod,</hi> you ſhall have <hi>another,</hi> and a <hi>third</hi> and a <hi>fourth.</hi> If you will not for all this turn to the Lord, I will yet puniſh you <hi>ſeven times more for your Iniquities, Levit.</hi> 26.18. In theſe Caſes, God doth not ſpare that he may ſpare; he doth not ſeem to have Mercy, that he may have Mercy; He doth not forbear his Rod, that we may forbear our ſins; He will not let us alone, that he may not be forced ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to abandon us: He will rebuke and chaſten, that we may not harden our ſelves unto our Eternal Ruine.</p>
               <p>Whenever you behold a wicked Perſon thrive and flouriſh in the World, when you ſee him proſper in his Trade, and boaſting of his Riches, priding himſelf in his Power; when you ſee him ſtrong and healthful, ſurrounded with all that is deſirable to fleſh and blood, flouriſhing with all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:188136:31"/>variety of outward Bleſſings, perſonal and family Advantages, &amp;c. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et neglect God, and wallow in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anner of carnal Impurities, reſtrain Prayer from the Almighty, in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and in his Cloſet, and live like a Beaſt, without God in the World; When you behold ſuch ſpectacles, think of the Accompliſhment of ſuch like Scriptures, where God threatens in Anger to forbear to puniſh ſuch and ſuch men. This is <hi>the firſt Method,</hi> his forbearing to afflict.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By taking away the External Means of Knowledg and Grace, or otherwiſe diſpoſing of Perſons ſo as they cannot enjoy ſuch ſeaſons. Acts 19.9. <hi>When divers were hardned, and believed not, but ſpake evil of that way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the multitude, he departed from them.</hi> God continues not the outward means in ſuch places, or the perſons remove into remote parts of the world, where the Goſpel of Chriſt is not known. Thus when lewd and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Youths have ſinned againſt God and their Parents, to that degree, that they know not what to do with them, they either go of themſelves, or are ſent into the <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>Army,</hi> or to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:188136:32"/>
                  <hi>Indies,</hi> to ſuch Places, where the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is not preached. And by this means men are left to walk in their own Counſels; The Publick Miniſtery of the Word being the ordinary Means of Sanctification. And ſo 'tis no wonder if they greedily fulfill their brutiſh Luſts. Therefore if God withdraw ſuch a Miniſtery from the Place where you reſide, or you run madly and without a call, or warrant, to dwell in ſuch places where it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, (I mean ſuch a Miniſtery as is proper to enlighten and awaken, and ſtrive with you in order to your Converſion and your ſalvation;) it is one ſtep to your being given over, and left of God, and to have the things of your Peace hid from your Eyes. I wiſh <hi>Merchants,</hi> and <hi>Traders,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> that have undutiful Children, and ſome Others, who are reſolved <hi>They will be Rich,</hi> would conſider this.</p>
               <p>But if you have ſat under a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing lively Miniſtry, but you begin to diſlike it; in that caſe it looks very ill. Eſpecially the more you were affected with it formerly, and now diſreliſh it, or deſpiſe it. In ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the means of holy Knowledge and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:188136:32"/>Sanctification not being continued, or improved, it looks fearful as to ſuch Perſons: More eſpecially if They be unaffected, and unconcerned it their own Danger in theſe Circumſtances.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is ſaid to pour upon men a Spirit of Slumber, and deep Sleep, to ſuffer them to harden their Hearts, and ſtupify their own Conſciences the more, by every thing they enjoy; ſo that though the external Means be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet none of the divine Meſſages will be received, nor the moſt uſeful Miniſtry do them any good: nor the Providential goodneſs of God lead them to Repentance. All their earthly poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and temporal Bleſſings ſhall become ſnares, and ſtumbling blocks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, behold, I will lay stumbling blocks before this People, and the fathers and the ſons together ſhall fall upon them: The neighbour and his friend ſhall periſh.</hi> But this is after they have wilfully hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened themſelves. So it was with <hi>Pharoah</hi> when he had obſtinately <hi>hardened his own Heart, Exod.</hi> 7.14.8. <hi>chap.</hi> 19, 32. <hi>ver.</hi> After that, upon his continued Obſtinacy, God declares that <hi>he harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him,</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi> 12. and 16. <hi>ver.</hi> And cauſed him to ſtand up, or <hi>raiſed him up,</hi> that is, kept him alive, when he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:188136:33"/>deſerved to be cut off by a quick and ſudden Deſtruction; for this very end, <hi>that he might ſhew in him his Power.</hi> So pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking was his former Obſtinacy, and Incorrigibleneſs. Thus are men the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cauſe, by choſen wilful Blindneſs and Hardneſs, before they are forſaken, and left of God under ſuch a Judgment.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another ſtep is God's righteous Refuſal to continue that Influence of the divine Spirit, with the external Means of Grace, which men have abuſed and forfeited. Without this Influence there cannot be a Day of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> under the Goſpel Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation: Both which are neceſſary to make our day of Grace. But when any People or Perſon have rebelled againſt God, and vexed his holy Spirit, he may ceaſe to ſtrive with their Hearts by any gracious Influence: When he hath knocked often, and they would not open; ſuch inward Motions of the Spirit, as they formerly had, they may have no more; and ſo they are forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of God. But whether <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> ſo as not to return again, is more than we can ſay of particular Perſons, till the Event ſhew it. But it is that which Men have reaſon to fear, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ordinary Methods of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:188136:33"/>Gods proceeding, who now diſobey the Voice of his Word and Spirit. He might Juſtly withdraw the Influence of his Spirit from them, and ſeal them up to Deſtruction; and ſo it is poſſible their Day of Grace may be ended <hi>before they dye;</hi> and their not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving or being converted, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly follow, <hi>John</hi> 12.39, 40.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another ſtep is, when <hi>God ſends ſtrong Deluſions, whereby men believe Lyes, that they may be damned,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. This is ſevere indeed, but being after obſtinate Refuſal of his Grace, it is righteous ſeverity. For this is threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Puniſhment of backſliding Chriſtian Churches, againſt ſuch who would not receive the Truth in the Love of it. <hi>The Deceived and the Deceiver are his, Job</hi> 12.16.</p>
               <p>Now God may do this two ways: <hi>Firſt,</hi> By permitting Deceivers, and falſe Teachers, to ſpeak and act at that rate of Cunning, and colour of Truth, that it is very difficult to reſiſt or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſnare. And therefore we read of the coming of the Man of ſin <hi>with all ſigns, and lying Wonders,</hi> or with Wonders to confirm thoſe Lyes. This God foretold and warned the <hi>Jews</hi> of before hand.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:188136:34"/>
               <p n="2">2. God may give Men up to ſtrong Deluſions, by taking away the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Reaſon and a clear Judgment, to diſtinguiſh between things that differ. Thus Men <hi>wreſt the holy Scriptures to their own Deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. Which they could not do without his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Permiſſion. And when the Gentiles had ſinned highly againſt the Light of Nature, God gave them over to <hi>a Reprobate Mind, Rom.</hi> 1.26. or to a mind uncapable of Judging, as the word imports; a blind unjudicious Mind, that could not examine, or diſtinguiſh between Truth and Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. This is as conſiſtent with the Juſtice of God (conſidering it as the Puniſhment of former Guilt,) as the depriving us of any of our ſenſes would be.</p>
               <p>And without ſome ſuch thing as this, it will be impoſſible to give an Account of the Growth, and Prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the many ridiculous, abſurd Doctrines, and Practices of <hi>Popery.</hi> It cannot otherwiſe be accounted for, that ſuch Fooleries as are to be found in their Opinions and Worſhip, ſhould ever be received, believed, complied, with, and pleaded for, by Men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of Judgment and Learning; But
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:188136:34"/>it is to be feared that they are <hi>given over to ſtrong Deluſions to believe Lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are many others that are no Papiſts, whom this may concern, who, after a great Profeſſion, have fallen back into ſecret Wickedneſs, and at laſt into more open Crimes, againſt Convictions and Reſolutions, Promiſes and former Experience. Many ſuch in the laſt Age, and ſome in this, have been thus left of God, to run into ſtrange Enthuſiaſm, and real Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, to receive the moſt extravagant, and ſometimes blaſphemous Opinions; to eſpouſe and plead for them, againſt the plaineſt Reaſon, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scripture that can be. But uſually it may be obſerved, the Doctrines they receive, and the new Lights they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, are ſuch as tend to Licentiouſneſs, to encourage the Gratification of their Luſts, that they can ſin on by the help of theſe Opinions, with greater Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Peace. This is another ſtep, whereby men are given up to their own Hearts Luſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LASTLY,</hi> When God gives ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Permiſſion to <hi>the Devil,</hi> the great Enemy of Souls, to exert his Power, and Malice in blinding and deſtroying Sinners.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:188136:35"/>
               <p>We do not ſufficiently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what we owe to Gods Reſtraint of <hi>Satan,</hi> that we are not more ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tempted to deny the Faith, and caſt off the yoke of Chriſt When the Spirit of the Lord departed from <hi>Saul,</hi> an Evil Spirit from the Lord is ſent to trouble and puniſh him, and <hi>Satan</hi> filled his heart with Rage and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14. Some evil Spirit had leave from God to ſeduce <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.21, 22. Who acted his part ſuccesfully to deceive and deſtroy. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid,</hi> ſays our Apoſtle, <hi>it is hid to them that are lost,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Whoſe eyes are blinded by the God of this World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HE is ready to do us all the miſchief he can, if God reſtrain him not. What a Power had he over <hi>the Bodies</hi> of ſome Men, in the days of our Saviour! He would manifeſt as much over their <hi>Souls</hi> too, if God did but give him leave. The Red Dragon went out to deceive the Nations, we read in the <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> As to thoſe who are judicially left of God, and given up to their own Hearts Luſts, it may come to this, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doth ſo; that God leaves them to the Power of <hi>Satan</hi> to deceive and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:188136:35"/>them, and <hi>they are led captive by him at his will.</hi> How diſmal muſt the Caſe of ſuch Perſons be! Which brings me to conſider.</p>
               <p n="3">III. THE Severity of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides what has been ſaid concerning it already, let me add a few Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Severity of this Judgment will appear, if we conſider that it is never inflicted but after many preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Provocations, upon habitual and obſtinate ſinners. For ſins againſt Light and Knowledge, preſumptuous and repeated Tranſgreſſions, ſuch for which there was no ſacrifice appointed under the Law, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Severity of this Judgment may be argued from the Subject of it, it falls upon <hi>the Soul,</hi> it doth eſpecially reſpect <hi>that,</hi> as its immediate Subject. The diſmal Effects of it reach to the Soul: The Beauty and Comelineſs of the Soul is hereby ſpoiled: For what more diſmal Spectacle can there be, than ſuch a man thus left of God? The Honour and Dignity of the Soul is hereby debaſed; for men given up to their own Hearts Luſts are almoſt trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into Beaſts.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:188136:36"/>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the moſt diſhonourable <hi>Slavery</hi> follows upon it. They are left under the Power and Rage of their own Luſts; and did you know what a <hi>Slavery</hi> that is, you would rather beg of <hi>God</hi> that you might fall into the Hands of the moſt barbarous and cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the World, than to be left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dominion of your own Luſts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe they are <hi>left to walk in their own Counſels,</hi> as the fruit of their being given up to their own Luſts. And theſe are, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The moſt fooliſh blind Guides that can be, that fill men with vain Projects and Deſigns. As the rich Fool in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke.</hi> 16. He would pull down his Barns, and build greater, and ſay, <hi>Soul take thine eaſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They are falſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Guides. They promiſe Peace and Happineſs, but procure nothing like it; Promiſe Eaſe and Reſt, but can by no means perform what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; but leave a man to wander and go aſtray unto his own Deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They are cruel and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Guides, as well as deceitful ones. Such Perſons will walk in the way that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:188136:36"/>leads to Deſtruction: He that walketh after his own Counſel, will find the End of that way to be Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Severity of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will appear, in that it can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be inflicted but <hi>in Anger.</hi> This is the Fruit of divine Wrath. All other Calamities and Afflictions may be the Fruit of Love, may be ſanctified for our good, may turn to our Advantage: But this Calamity has no ſuch Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and no ſuch Effect. A man may be given up to <hi>Satan</hi> for the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Fleſh, that the Soul may be ſaved; But to be given up to ſin is a thouſand times worſe, becauſe that is the Fruit of Divine Anger, in order to the Damnation of the Soul. Here God wounds like an Enemy, and like a cruel one: And we may boldly ſay, <hi>God never puniſhed any Man or Woman, with this Spiritual Judgment, in Kindneſs and Love.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:188136:37"/>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:188136:37"/>
               <head>The Third Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſalm LXXXI. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So I gave them up to their own Hearts luſts: and they walked in their own Counſels.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>UPON the Rehearſal of ſome terrible Threatning, when Judgment is denounced, or ſignified to be approaching, but the particular Perſons are not named, who are to be the Subjects of it, we may uſe the Words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel, chap.</hi> 4.29. Before he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to the King the Import and ſenſe of his ominous Dream; <hi>The Dream be to them that hate thee, O King! and the Interpretation thereof unto thine. Enemies.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:188136:38"/>But ſuch is the Severity and Horrour of this threatned Judgment in the Text, that we ſhould not, we ought not to wiſh ſo much Evil to our worſt Enemies; but do what we can to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. For of all Calamities that can be threatned, or inflicted in this World, what can be worſe than for a Man to be given up to his own Luſts, and left to walk in his own Counſels? Two or three things we may obſerve by way of <hi>general Inference,</hi> before I ſpeak to ſome particular Caſes and Queſtions that relate hereto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. HOW Much to be pitied is the Ignorance and Folly of ſinners, that are afraid of any other Calamity more than this. <hi>I gave 'em up to their own Hearts Lusts,</hi> is a thouſand times worſe than if God had given 'em up to the <hi>Syrians</hi> to ſpoil 'em, or to their moſt enraged Adverſaries to oppreſs 'em. Men are ready to quake and tremble, and their Hearts to be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the Trees of the Wood are moved with the Wind, if a thick or dark Cloud hover over them, as to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or private Affairs. If their Health and Eaſe, their Liberties and Eſtates, their outward Priviledges and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:188136:38"/>are threatened and endangered, they preſently apprehend themſelves concerned to look about them, and do their utmoſt to prevent it. But if ſin be the greateſt Enemy, to be given up to ſin is the greateſt Judgment, and ſhould be more feared than Plague, or Peſtilence, or Famine, or War, or any of thoſe Calamities that Nations and Perſons do commonly dread as moſt Formidable Evils.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it the greateſt Judgment to be given up to our own Hearts Luſts? How unreaſonable is the Diſpleaſure and Anger of Men at the ſharpeſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Divine Grace, that would bring them to Repentance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prevent this ſad Cataſtrophe? The moſt ſmart Reproofs of the Word; the moſt cloſe Exhortations, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions of Miniſters, that are now accounted troubleſome, the moſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and uneaſy Convictions of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and the moſt afflictive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes of Providence too, that have this merciful Deſign and Tendency, they are the real Effects of Kindneſs, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive of a greater Miſchief, even this, of being left of God, and given up to our own Hearts Luſts.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:188136:39"/>
               <p>What Enemies therefore are they to their own Intereſt, who uſe ſuch Language as that of the Stubborn <hi>Jews, Iſa.</hi> 30.10. ſaying to the Prophets, <hi>Prophecie not unto us Right things, ſpeak unto us ſmooth things, and prophecie Deceits.</hi> Till God in righteous Judgment reſolve, and ſay, as he did afterwards, <hi>Ezek</hi> 3.26. <hi>Thou ſhalt no longer be unto them a Reprover, Thou ſhalt be dumb, and thy Tongue cleave to the Roof of thy mouth, for they are a rebellious Houſe.</hi> When ſuch as would convince and awaken Men by neceſſary Reproofs, are diſlik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their Preaching reckoned <hi>a Burden,</hi> becauſe <hi>the Earth is tormented with their Words, Revel.</hi> 11.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. HOW wretched and dangerous is their Miſtake, who think their Caſe good, becauſe their <hi>Conſciences</hi> now trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them no more. They have ſinned themſelves into ſuch hardneſs of Heart, and ſearedneſs of Conſcience, under ſuch Judicial Blindneſs and ſtupidity, that the ſin, which was formerly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom as a Mountain, they now feel not; they bewail it not. <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that did rebuke them, is now ſilent and faſt aſleep. All things are at peace with them, <hi>they ſay,</hi> and they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:188136:39"/>are glad of it, and ſo is the Devil too.</p>
               <p>God lets them proſper in the World, they have no rub in their way, to Hell. But in the mean time he hath given them over, that they ſhall not be ſmitten any more: that they ſhall not be troubled with the ſtrivings of his Spirit any more. Neither Word nor Rod ſhall do them good more. They applaud themſelves in this, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in it: But if to be given up to our own Hearts Luſts be the greateſt Judgment, there is no ſtorm more diſmal than ſuch a Calm, or more to be dreaded. No Trouble but is better than ſuch Peace: No Sickneſs but is preferable to ſuch Health: No Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row but is rather to be choſen than ſuch mad Joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doubt.</hi> 1. BUT becauſe I would not break the bruiſed Reed, or quench the ſmoking Flax, or ſadden the Hearts of thoſe whom God would not have ſaddened; but rather awaken the Joy, and aſſiſt the Conſolation, and promote the ſpiritual Peace of thoſe unto whom it doth of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: I ſhall therefore conſider ſome of the Doubts, and Objections of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:188136:40"/>weak, or melancholy, dejected Chriſtians, who on all Occaſions argue againſt themſelves, and conclude hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their own State, from every word of Threatening and Terrour againſt the Ungodly: As melancholy People can hardly hear any Diſeaſe talked of or deſcribed, but they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently imagin they have ſome of the Symptoms of it in their Caſe.</p>
               <p>WHAT I have ſaid of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Terrour of this Judgment, and of the Methods o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Divine Juſtice in the Execution of it, may make ſome ready to ſay.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I fear leſt God hath given me up, for I have reſiſted many of the ſtrivings of the Spirit of Grace, and now I think he doth not ſtrive with me any more. I have been under the Rod, and not bettered by it, the Spirit of ſlumber and of a deep ſleep ſeems to poſſeſs me. I have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood many Calls to Repentance, and ſtifled many Convictions of Conſcience, and contradicted many good Reſolutions, and broken many Vows and Promiſes; I have back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliden and revolted from God after
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:188136:40"/>very hopeful Beginnings: Therefore the Puniſhment of Apoſtates may Juſtly be inflected on me. I, that have caſted the good Word of God, and of the Powers of the World to come, may well fear being left of God, ſo as it ſhould be impoſſible for me to be renewed by Repentance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Day of Grace is over, ſaith Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my accepted Time</hi> paſt, there is nothing ſo bad but I may Juſtly fear it: For I find I grow worſe and worſe, inſtead of making progreſs in Holineſs: whereas if my Grace were true it would be growing. But I find my Corruptions exceeding ſtrong, my heart very dead and hard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doubtleſs God has withdrawn his Spirit from me, will <hi>Another ſay,</hi> I have not the Covenant Bleſſing of a ſoft Heart, a Heart of Fleſh; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not weep a Tear for my ſins, as once I could: I am good for nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for any ſpiritual Duty; None in the World have ſuch a treacherous vile abominable Heart as I have, I am afraid God has given me over;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:188136:41"/>I do not know but I may have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>the ſin unto Death,</hi> the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin, the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which ſhall never be forgiven.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> THIS being a complicated Caſe, comprehending the objections of ſeveral People, wherein are ſome things that deſerve <hi>Pity,</hi> and others that need <hi>Reproof;</hi> there being ſomewhat very ſad in it, and ſomewhat very faulty too; It is manifeſt that my Reply muſt be mixed: It muſt in part be monitory and reprehenſive, and in part conſolatory. For Reproof and Counſel are neceſſary, as well as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragment and Comfort. I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to intermix both; in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars, by way of Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. CONSIDER, That to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der very great Darkneſs, Doubts, and Fears, ſo as to create much Trouble and Torment to your ſelves, will not of it ſelf conclude your Caſe deſperate, and your Souls finally forſaken. There are many Reaſons for Soul trouble, the Children of Light may walk in Darkneſs. You may Judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn your ſelves for Unbelievers and Reprobates, and yet unjuſtly do ſo.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:188136:41"/>You may refuſe to be comforted, and ſay all that the Devil ſpeaks againſt you to be true, and that it is impoſſible for ſuch a one, <hi>as you,</hi> to find Mercy: And yet all this may be falſe and faulty, and thoſe Clouds may afterwards va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, Light appear, and Joy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. The Examples in Scripture, and the Experience of every Age will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this.</p>
               <p>It may be your miſtake about the Nature of <hi>Faith,</hi> and make it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> not diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>direct</hi> and the <hi>reflex Act</hi> of Faith. Whereas if true Faith conſiſt in <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> and without Faith there is no ſalvation; A Man muſt be aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his Salvation, or elſe he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be damned. And this is to ſuppoſe that a Man muſt <hi>Firſt</hi> be ſure of Heaven, before he can be capable of it. But you may be in Chriſt, and have the Image of Chriſt, and the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his Children, and ſhall be kept by the Power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; though for a time you may diſtruſt, and deſpair of it, walk mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and refuſe to be comforted. Your own Doubts and Fears will not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:188136:42"/>prove that you are given over, but rather the Contrary. For,</p>
               <p n="2">II. If you are given up to your own Hearts Luſts, how is it that you thus mourn, and greive at the Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Fear of it? Do you not value his Favour more than Life? And dread his Diſpleaſure more than Death? and fear nothing more than that God ſhould forſake you? And is it likely that <hi>Such</hi> are left of God, who hereby diſcover that they love him in Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Your very Solicitude, and Fear, and Diſquiet, leſt God ſhould finally reject you, and caſt you off, is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that <hi>he hath not;</hi> and, if you continue of this Mind, that <hi>he never will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Believe it, <hi>O doubting Chriſtian,</hi> if thou art from thy Soul unwilling to leave God, and of all things in the World doſt dread and deprecate his leaving thee, He hath not left thee, or given thee over. For be aſſured of this, <hi>God never did, or will forſake any, but thoſe who firſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſake him, and are unwilling to Return.</hi> Where do you ever find, or how can it poſſibly be, that ſuch a Mans Day of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:188136:42"/>Grace is paſt, and the time of his Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over, that God hath Judicially left him, and given him up, who values the Preſence of God, and fears no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than to Sin againſt him, or to provoke him to caſt him off? Is ſuch a Man loſt, and given over, who thirſteth after God, and can be ſatisfied with nothing ſhort of him? Where do you ever find, that God did ever finally leave a Man, and leave any ſuch Grace behind him?</p>
               <p>Is ſuch a Man <hi>loſt,</hi> and given up by God? Who prefers the Light of his Countenance before Corn, and Wine, and Oil, and all the Riches, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Honours of the World; Who had rather live in the moſt mean miſerable afflictive Condition on Earth, with the Love and Favour of God, than enjoy the greateſt Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all things without it. I ſhall amplifie this more preſently under the <hi>ſixth</hi> Head.</p>
               <p n="3">III. LET me ask you, Are you not reſolved to hold on your Fight and Warfare againſt ſin? To continue and maintain your Conflict, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:188136:43"/>all your Doubts, and all your Complaints? You may ſometimes take <hi>being tempted</hi> for being <hi>overcome.</hi> But though Temptations have been too prevalent, and many of your Reſolutions and Purpoſes againſt ſin have been broken; Are you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſtruggle no more, to reſiſt no longer? Dare you ſay upon ſerious Deliberation, <q>Well, now I ſee my Caſe is hopeleſs, I will uſe no more Means againſt the Devil and ſin, I will pray to God no more, I will hear, and read his Word no more, I will attend upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Goſpel no longer, it is all to no purpoſe?</q> I know you durſt not ſay this, nor talk at this rate.</p>
               <p>Beſides, when you have fallen into ſin through the Prevalency of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, do you not make haſte to riſe again by bitter Repentance? Do you not freely confeſs, and aggravate your ſins in the Preſence of God, and not palliate, cover, or excuſe them? Are you not uneaſy, and reſtleſs under your Declenſions? Deſirous to make your Peace with God, and to be reconciled through Chriſt? Do you not double
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:188136:43"/>your Guard, and Watch afterwards? Do you not ſtill love Holineſs, and the Image of God, wherever you ſee it? Do you not check, and chide, and find fault with your ſelves, for your ungrateful Carriage to the God of Love? Are you not diſpleaſed with your ſelves? And aſhamed of your ſelves? And glad of any Help and Aſſiſtance that leads to your Recovery? If this be your Caſe, be aſſured your Day of Grace is not paſt, you are not left of God.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. YOU ſay, you cannot weep, and mourn, and expreſs your Repentance, as formerly, and as ſome others you know do; Yet conſider that it is the hatred of ſin and watchfulneſs againſt it, that is the trueſt ſign of Repentance and godly ſorrow. For to uſe the words of Mr. <hi>B. He that will be at the greateſt Coſt and Pains to be rid of ſin, or that he had not ſinned, or that he might ſin no more, though he have not ſuch command of Tears as Others, is the trueſt Penitent.</hi> You cannot weep for ſin as Others, but you would give all the World to be rid of ſin; you could wiſh that when
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:188136:44"/>you had diſhonoured God by <hi>Sin,</hi> you had ſpent that time in <hi>Suffering,</hi> and if it were to do again, upon the ſame Reaſons and Inducements, you would not do it. And if you might but pleaſe and obey God more than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and be kept from diſobeying him, you would be content with any thing Judge your ſelves by this.</p>
               <p>Beſides
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See</hi> Dr: <hi>Collings Cordial for a Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul, part</hi> 1. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2.</note> God hath not told us juſt what degree and meaſure of Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Sorrow for ſin is abſolutely needful. Some have more, and others leſs even of true Penitents.</p>
               <p>TAKE heed of miſtaking the Caſe concerning <hi>the Day of Grace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>over,</hi> and ſinners being finally left of God. For it is never true in this Life, that any are ſo left of God, and their Day of Grace ſo over, as that if they truly repent, and turn to him, he will not accept them. This would be againſt the whole tenour of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Covenant: For whoſoever turns to God by true Repentance, and Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>ſhall not periſh but have eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:188136:44"/>
               <p>But there is another ſenſe of ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſſions, that is, when men have ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng reſiſted the Spirit, and refuſed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffers of Gods Grace, and rejected the Yoke and Government of Chriſt, that God reſolves <hi>to let them alone,</hi> never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o give them the prevailing Grace of his Spirit, but in righteous Judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o abandon them to their own Hearts Luſts, to walk in their own Counſels.</p>
               <p>Becauſe they would not turn at my Reproof, <hi>they ſhall call, but I will not anſwer, ſeek me earneſtly, but not find me, Prov.</hi> 1.28. If men harden their Hearts, and will not hear and obey the voice of God, He may ſware in his Wrath, that they ſhall not enter into his Reſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.11.15, 18. <hi>Num.</hi> 12.22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. It may be this very day, or hour while now thou art called by God to Turn and Live, if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe <hi>now,</hi> thy Day may be over, and paſt for ever. To morrow God may ſay, <hi>Let him Alone, he ſhall not be purged, he ſhall dye in his ſins. Iſa.</hi> 42.14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17. This is a poſſible Caſe, but who can tell when it is thus? How can this be known of particular Perſons when it is ſo, though ſome Approach
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:188136:45"/>nearer to it than Others? How can it poſitively be ſaid of any, that God will never give ſuch Perſons Repentance unto Life? You may be ſure, that if you find your Hearts Penitent, and willing to return to him, that it doth not reach you: It is not your Caſe. Therefore,</p>
               <p n="6">VI. YOU that thus complain and fear, have you not many of the Fruits of the Spirit viſible, and manifeſt in you? Therefore the Spirit of Chriſt hath not left you; God hath not given you over. Do you not eſteem and prize the GRACE of the Goſpel? Do you not cry to Heaven for the Spirit of <hi>Grace?</hi> Are you not earneſt in the ſeeking the Spirit of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from day to day? Whence is it, but from <hi>Grace,</hi> that you have an Heart to prize and ſeek it? They that have outſtood the Day of Grace, they deſpiſe it; they are ſunk into Carnality, and Forgetfulneſs of God; they are inſenſible, and ſtupid, and unconcerned about <hi>his Grace.</hi> But for you that value it, and ſeek it, your Day of Grace cannot be over: For it is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:188136:45"/>from <hi>Common Grace,</hi> at leaſt, which has a tendency to <hi>Special,</hi> and ſhows your Caſe not to be like thoſe, who are given up of God.</p>
               <p>But with moſt that thus complain, there is more than common Grace: There are Fruits of ſpecial Grace viſible. You do unfeignedly Repent, and mourn for Sin; and deſire to give up your ſelves to Chriſt. Now what but <hi>Grace</hi> hath made you to ſee the evil of ſin, and hate it? What but <hi>Grace</hi> hath made you willing to Accept of Chriſt, for your Lord and Saviour? What but <hi>Grace</hi> has made you value the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, and a holy Heart and Life, above all the World? How is it that you are brought to love God, and delight in him, to ſeek after him, and deſire to pleaſe him, and to be troubled that you can do ſo no more, no better? For ſuch as you to ſay <hi>your Day of Grace is over,</hi> is as abſurd, as one expreſſeth it, as for a Man to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Aſſemblies, and hear the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and then go away lamenting that the Sermon was done before he came. You have received that Grace, which you complain you want.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:188136:46"/>
               <p>You know 'tis otherwiſe with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Were you like them; Did you find your Luſts and Paſſions lead you captive at their pleaſure; had you no Affections ſtirring after God, and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; did you deſpiſe Chriſt, and all Regard and Duty to him; and could not perſwade your ſelves to hear, or read, or pray, or think of another World, or do any thing to provide for it, you might then fear indeed what the iſſue of your Caſe would be.</p>
               <p>But that is not the Caſe I am now ſpeaking of; nor of any, I hope, that now hear me, your Appearance in theſe Aſſemblies is ſome ſign of the contrary: And though as yet you may be unconverted, and unſanctified, if you are ſo far Awake as to look after Reconciliation to God; if you are touched with a ſenſe of your ſin and Danger, ſo as to deſire to be aſſiſted, and enabled to Repent, and turn to the Lord; how bad ſoever your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe be, it is <hi>not Deſperate,</hi> and <hi>Remedileſs:</hi> For you are in the way of Mercy, and nothing but your own wilful, impenitent refuſal of Mercy, can deprive you of it.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:188136:46"/>
               <p n="7">VII. As to the Complaint of <hi>an Hard Heart,</hi> Remember it is the <hi>Impenitent,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nperſwadable Heart</hi> that is the only hard Heart you need to fear. They that are obſtinate, and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, intractable and incorrigible; as the People of the <hi>Jews</hi> were, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarded the divine Threatnings or Promiſes, or minded his Precepts; Theſe are they that are under <hi>Hardneſs of Heart.</hi> This is the Judgment you ought to fear, to be left under ſuch a Temper. But you find it otherwiſe with you, that the voice of God doth awe and command you: Your Wills are bowed unto Subjection to him; you are willing to take upon you the Yoke of Chriſt, or have taken it; and renouncing all Competitors, you deſire to chuſe Chriſt for your Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and that God in Chriſt ſhould be your Ruler, and your Felicity. If it be thus, you may be ſure you are not left of God.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. THAT Sight of ſin, and ſenſe of the Burthen of Corruption, which you complain of, as the Ground of your fear, will argue the direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:188136:47"/>to what you alledge it for. For ſin has always the greateſt ſtrength where the ſinner is the leaſt Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive and Senſible of it. There is more hope of a ſenſible Patient, that feels his ſickneſs, and complains of it, than of one that feels nothing, but is confident all is well. Is not their Caſe much worſe, who feel nothing of the Evil of ſin, to whom the Power of it is not troubleſome, nor the Pollution of it lothſom, nor the Guilt of it but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenfom? While it is otherwiſe with you, you may be aſſured you are not given over, and left of God, and your Day of Grace paſt: it is yet <hi>Day</hi> with you or elſe how came you by ſo much <hi>Light</hi> to ſee the evil of ſin more than formerly and to ſee ſo many things to be ſin, which before you did not?</p>
               <p>Though there may and will be a Conflict between Fleſh and Spirit, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Grace, in the beſt, while in this World; yet which Party doſt thou ſide with? Which has thy moſt willing Conſent? Which way is thy prevailing Deſire, Love, and Choice? Doſt thou not bewail the Body of ſin and Death? And wiſh to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:188136:47"/>be delivered from Corruption more perfectly? To gain a more intire Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Doſt thou not watch, and wreſtle, and ſtrive, and pray againſt it from day to day? Is this the true ſtate of thy Caſe? Then never think thou art left of God.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Some</hi> of you, I may go further; and deſire you to look back upon your former Humiliations for ſin, when <hi>Firſt</hi> you turned to God. Though all have not the ſame ſenſible Degree of Humiliation; yet hath not the Spirit of Grace convinced you of the Holineſs and Equity of the Law of God? And of your own wretched, accurſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition under the Guilt of ſin? Have you not been brought, to tremble at the thoughts of his righteous Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence? So as to diſreliſh all the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this World, by reaſon of the ſenſe of ſin; ſeeing no way out of this Perplexity, but by the free, and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable Mercy of God in Chriſt; and therefore Renouncing all things that might ſeparate between Chriſt and thee, ready to part with all thy Luſts, and Pleaſures, and Profits, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Thou wert made willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:188136:48"/>of his Mercy on his own Terms; crying earneſtly for pardoning, and ſanctifying Grace, acknowledging thy Unworthineſs of the leaſt Favour; owning the righteouſneſs of God, if he ſhould condemn thee; and yet, upon the Invitation and Call of the Goſpel, looking up to his Mercy-ſeat with Hope, Reſolving there to anchor and take no Denial.</p>
               <p>Now after all this, and <hi>the Covenant Dedication</hi> of your ſelves to God in Chriſt, that followed upon it, and ſome Calmneſs and ſtability of Soul conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thereto, will you queſtion all again? Becauſe Corruption is not quite mortified, nor Sin quite deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Even that ſenſe of remaining Sin that you make the matter of your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt your ſelves, is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for you, and will conclude the Contrary to what you alledge it for.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. THO You cannot ſay ſo much, as to preſent ſenſe, of your Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſin and Loathing of it, as you deſire; yet examine your ſelves as to <hi>the Sins of Others,</hi> and what ſenſe you
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:188136:48"/>have of the Diſhonour of God by them. We may ſometimes gather matter of Comfort this way, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our own Sincerity, and Love to God, when we cannot ſo well have it nearer home. As bad as thou art, or thinkeſt thy ſelf to be: Art thou not tender of the Honour of God? Art thou not concerned for his Intereſt and Glory? Doth not thy ſoul trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and thine Heart ake when the Being of God is denied, or his Sacred Name blaſphemed, or the Glory of the Mediator Struck at, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Goſpel queſtioned, by the Atheiſts, and Saduces, and Infidels of the Age? Or the Progreſs of it obſtracted?</p>
               <p>Doth not thy Heart riſe within thee, if thou happen into wicked Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, where the Word of God, his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, his Miniſters, and Servants are vilified and reproached, and bold Impieties vented, and vile Impurities boaſted of? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. BUT I do <hi>not Grow,</hi> I rather wax worſe, will ſome ſay. As to that, Conſider, that though there be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:188136:49"/>Promiſes, and Examples of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Grace, that ſhew what is Gods uſual way, and the Proper Tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Spiritual Life; yet thoſe Promiſes are not ſo Abſolute, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Condition, as that there is no true Believer who doth not alwaies grow in <hi>Grace:</hi> For Experience ſhews, that ſome decline and loſe their firſt Fervour, and need to be awakened to Repentance. The Promiſes of Growth and Faithfulneſs are not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, but depend on the Improvement of Grace received, and the Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of many Duties, with great watchfulneſs and Diligence in our whole Chriſtian Courſe. And many Chriſtians, live not up to the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Accompliſhment of ſuch Promiſes, as concern the Growth and thriving of Spiritual Life. They decay, and decline through their own Carleſneſs, and Negligence.</p>
               <p>Senſible Affections be ſure, and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Encreaſe in that reſpect, is not the true Meaſure, whereby to Judge of growth in Grace. For different Ages, and Tempers, and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our condition in the world
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:188136:49"/>will make a great Difference in ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Affections.</p>
               <p>You may grow in Grace, by a more Judicious Eſteem, and value of God and Holineſs, Love to Chriſt and his Grace, and Glory, ſo as it may be harder for the Devil to draw you off from God, than before; even when you think you do not grow, you may be more ſtable and reſolved, though not ſo lively and affectionate. And the decay of natural ſtrength, and vigor of parts by old age or ſickneſs, may make a Difference with ſome. Your Humility, your ſelf denial, and Patience may encreaſe, when you think otherwiſe. And he who grows <hi>more humble</hi> thrives in every other Grace, whether he believe it, and take notice of it or no. But if you are declin'd, the Remedy muſt be to Awake, and to uſe Gods appointed Means to make you, grow in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. You cannot thereupon conclude that you have no Grace, much leſs that you are left of God, and given over. Such as enquire not whether they grow or decay, who
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:188136:50"/>have little or no Concern about their own Caſe as to theſe things, have moſt reaſon to fear it of themſelves, whilſt ſuch as do really grow, for a time, may not diſcern it. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times others may obſerve it, when they themſelves diſown it, or perceive it not.</p>
               <p>But if you are under ſome declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Remember the cauſe, that it is from ſloth and negligence in the uſe of God's appointed means for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; from the want of daily Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of ſin, and Watchfulneſs againſt it; from countenacing ſome Luſt, ſo that its power is encreaſed, ſuffering the Love of the World to ſteal upon you, and conforming to it; giving way to Formality, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſneſs in divine Worſhip, and the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion; and Apply the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy by Repentance, Mortification, and doing your firſt works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1,2. But make not haſty, unjuſt Concluſions concerning your final ſtate.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. MOREOVER Conſider, there may be much more of Blame and Faultineſs, of Guilt and ſin, in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:188136:50"/>your unbelieving Objections, and Deſpondency, than you are aware of. Therefore while you complain of ſin, take heed you do not encreaſe, and add to your ſin by diſobeying the command of God to <hi>Believe</hi> and <hi>Hope.</hi> God hath made <hi>Hope</hi> a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Duty, and Gods Command were enough, if there were nothing elſe in your Caſe. Your <hi>Deſpair,</hi> as if your Caſe were deſperate, and your Condition hopeleſs, that God had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally given you over, is a plain <hi>ſin:</hi> And will you juſtifie it? He obliges you to <hi>hope;</hi> he hath not bid the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or the damned to hope, as he hath commanded you. It is <hi>by hope we are ſaved;</hi> and he takes Pleaſure in them that hope in his Mercy.</p>
               <p>But to convince you of this ſin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a Repreſentation of the bleſſed God your Objection makes, as if he were not a God of Grace, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Inquity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin, upon Repentance, which is what he hath declared concerning himſelf. Now is it not a ſin to believe God to be ſuch an one, as is directly contrary to the Character he has given of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:188136:51"/>That though I never ſo much deſire his Favour, and value it as my Life; though I deſire to my utmoſt to comport with his Mind and Will, ſo far as he hath, or ſhall reveal it to me; to believe that yet he hath caſt me off, or will caſt me off: What a ſad Account of God does this give? What a Reproach upon him would this bring? Is not this to take the Devils Repreſentation of him to be truer than his own?</p>
               <p>There is likewiſe further ſin in your Objection, and Doubt, by miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Tenor of <hi>the Goſpel Covenant.</hi> Whereas <hi>that</hi> ſays, Take God in Chriſt for your God, and give up your ſelves to be his, and he is, and will be yours; you add ſomething more out of your own Head as neceſſary, and ſo alter the Terms of Life and Death. And what is this but to make a new Goſpel? The Bleſſed God hath ſaid, on ſuch Terms Souls ſhall be ſaved, you add others as neceſſary: And ſay, I ſhall never be ſaved, unleſs it be thus and thus with me; which God hath never ſaid. Though I do accept God for my God, and Chriſt for my Saviour,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:188136:51"/>and conſent to be his, and endeavour to pleaſe him, yet he will not ſave me. This is to give God the Lye, and there is more Guilt in it than we think. Therefore.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. LAY this as a Foundation Truth, and keep it, That <hi>you can never be more willing to Come to Chriſt, than he is to Receive you.</hi> If you think otherwiſe, your ſeeming Humility in Doubting hath much of Pride in it. If you are willing to have Chriſt and his Grace on his Terms, <hi>He is yours.</hi> If you are willing to have Chriſt for your Saviour, and your King, <hi>to receive him as Chriſt Jeſus the Lord;</hi> and the bleſſed Spirit as your Sanctifier; and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have his Favour, and Love, and his holy Image, than all the riches of this World; you are then <hi>His:</hi> If your Willingneſs be <hi>prevailing,</hi> and more than your Unwillingneſs.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be aſſured, <hi>is Willing;</hi> He hath firſt ſhown his Willingneſs, He dyed to manifeſt it, and hath drawn up, procured, and publiſhed a Covenant of Grace, wherein he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares <hi>his Conſent,</hi> and calls for <hi>yours.</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:188136:52"/>Therefore if there be not a Covenant Union unto Eternal Life between him and you, it is through <hi>your</hi> Refuſal, not his.</p>
               <p>Now if you are <hi>not willing</hi> to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his offered Grace, to be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by him, and bleſſed in him; why do you complain, for the want of that which you would not have, and are not willing of? For I tell you again, <hi>He is willing</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and Accept you, and to be <hi>Yours</hi> in an Everlaſting Covenant never to be broken, if you are ſincerely <hi>Willing</hi> to be <hi>His Covenant Servants.</hi> Moreover,</p>
               <p n="12">XII. AS to the Doubt concerning <hi>the ſin against the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> I think ſuch as make that Objection do not well underſtand wherein it lyes. Read the 12th of <hi>Matthew</hi> throughout, and <hi>Mark</hi> 3.28, 29, 30. And you will find that the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt never to be forgiven, was to this purpoſe; That when, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Miracles of Chriſt, which confirmed his divine Commiſſion, and proved him to be the Meſſiah, They
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:188136:52"/>who ſaw thoſe Miracles of Chriſt, and could not deny them to be true; yet did not believe him to be the Son of God, or his Doctrine to be true, though atteſted by thoſe Miracles. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than own him to be the Chriſt, they blaſphemouſly aſcribed his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles unto the Agency' of the Devil, the unclean Spirit; That were wrought by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>They therefore who own Chriſt to be the Meſſiah, and his Goſpel to be true; who do not take him for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, but acknowledge him as their Lord, and honour and worſhip him as the Chriſt of God; they are not Guilty of the ſin there mentioned, called <hi>The ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deny not but ſome may be guilty in our days of ſuch Sins, as make <hi>Approaches</hi> unto this, and are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like it; As when, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clear Evidence of the Truth of the Goſpel, Men reſiſt the Light, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt it, and turn open Apoſtates, and Perſecutors, if not down right profeſſed Infidels. But the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, there deſcribed by the Evangeliſt, ſeems to imply a Man's
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:188136:53"/>taking Chriſt for a Deceiver. Be ſure none who own the Goſpel to be true, and Chriſt to be the Saviour of fallen ſinners, are guilty of that Sin, though they may make dangerous Approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to it.</p>
               <p>Much leſs are they Guilty of it, who <hi>fear</hi> the guilt of this ſin: But ſuch doubting fearful Perſons, who make this Queſtion concerning themſelves, becauſe of ſome blaſphemous Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Satan,</hi> &amp;c. They would have been afraid of the Guilt of any other ſin as well as of this, if they had ever heard, or read ſuch dreadful things declared againſt any Other ſin, as againſt This: But they ſeem not to underſtand the Nature of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See Mr.</hi> Howe's <hi>Append. to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Tears.</hi>
                  </note> I do not deny but there may alſo be an <hi>equivalent Evidence</hi> of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt, and of the Truth of the Goſpel, that the Infidels of our Age may ſin againſt; <hi>Equivalent,</hi> I ſay, to what <hi>the Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> who where guilty of this ſin, did ſin againſt. And therefore our modern <hi>Deists,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:188136:53"/>who reproach the bleſſed Redeemer, and the Holy Spirit of God, had need look to it, leſt they approach unto the unpardonable ſin, and God ſhould give them over to their own Hearts <hi>Luſts.</hi> But as to poor doubting Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that fear they are guilty of the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, mentioned in the Goſpel, It is plain enough, that they fearing the Guilt of it are not in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of it for the preſent, or like to be ſo.</p>
               <p>LASTLY, To bring the whole matter to a ſhort Iſſue, and to put it out of queſtion, <hi>that your day of Grace is not over,</hi> and that God hath not left you, or given you over to your own Hearts Luſts; I do <hi>now</hi> tender you the Grace and Salvation purchaſed by Chriſt in his Name. If <hi>now</hi> you are heartily willing to accept it, the Caſe is determined: and determined in the beſt manner that can be. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to put all out of doubt, <hi>Accept the preſent offer of Gods Grace,</hi> which is this day made you. Oppoſe not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your ſins paſt, or the Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your preſent Unworthineſs, but penitently, and humbly, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:188136:54"/>thankfully accept the Pardon that is offered you in the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Do you think, in contradiction to the whole Goſpel, that your ſins are ſo many, or ſo great, that Chriſt did not, could not ſatisfie for them, and that he will not forgive them, if you Repent, and turn to God, and Believe on the Name of his Son? You are condemned by the Law; Chriſt came to ſave ſinners, and ſuch as were loſt; and he requires no Worthineſs, or Price in your Hands, but that you unfeignedly Conſent to be his, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept an offered Saviour, and his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the Ends and Uſes of the Covenant of Grace: That he may illuminate and teach you, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and guide you, govern and rule you, by his Word and Spirit. This is the <hi>Condition</hi> of your Title to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt be the <hi>Evidence</hi> of your Title, and ſhould be a ſatisfactory one.</p>
               <p>But if you are Unwilling to forſake ſin, and return to God by Jeſus Chriſt; if you are unwilling to receive him as your Teacher, Sanctifier, Saviour
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:188136:54"/>and Lord; you have reaſon to doubt your ſtate indeed, or rather the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is <hi>paſt doubt,</hi> you are unſanctified, and as yet unreconciled to God.</p>
               <p>Whoever thereſore, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their former Reſiſtance of the Spirit, ſtifling Convictions, violat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their good Reſolutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do queſtion their State, whether God hath not given them over; yet let them Conſider they are <hi>now</hi> invited, and entreated to put it out of queſtion that their Day of Grace is not paſt, by letting this be <hi>Their Accepted time, the Day of their Salvation;</hi> by now hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily accepting an offered Saviour, and giving up themſelves unto him. And then, notwithſtanding all your form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Refuſals of his Mercy and Grace, if <hi>now</hi> at laſt you will return and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and take his yoke upon you; there is Eaſe, and Reſt, and Pardon, and Comfort, and Life, Eternal Life to be had.</p>
               <p>To conclude, Inſtead of Doubting, and Complaining, and queſtioning any longer, Reduce all that which is <hi>Doubtful</hi> with you, to that which is <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Certain.</hi> It is certain that God hath ſent his Son into the World
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:188136:55"/>to ſave ſinners; It is certain that you are ſome of thoſe loſt, miſerable, guilty Creatures that need this Salvation; It is certain that he has publiſhed the glad Tidings of the Goſpel to ſuch, that <hi>whoever believeth ſhall be ſaved; Is is</hi> certain that God cannot lye, it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inconſiſtent with his Nature, that ſuch as come to him in the Exerciſe of Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould not be Accepted with him.</p>
               <p>Therefore diſpute, and queſtion, and complain no longer how matters have been, or how they are with you, but come in upon the Call and Invitation of the Goſpel Grace: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Covenant thou haſt made with God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt in Baptiſm; Reſign, yield and give up thy ſelf with all thy Heart and Soul to be his, reſolving that thou wilt throw thy ſelf into the Arms of his Love, and Mercy, becauſe it is the Command of God that you believe on his Son; Reſolve that through his Mercy and Grace, by the help of his Spirit of Grace, you will <hi>now</hi> do ſo, whatever come of it.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:188136:55"/>
               <p>Do not perplex your ſelves about the Queſtion, whether you did it not <hi>formerly,</hi> four, or five, or ten years ago? But do it again; Bleſſing God that you <hi>may now</hi> do it; that he has not repealed his Goſpel, and that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will repeal it to the end of the World. I may Accept of his Son now, as well as ſo many years ago. Bleſſed be God, the Invitation, the Command, the Promiſe is the ſame <hi>now</hi> as it was then; And to as many as Receive him, he will give the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to become the Sons of God, even to as many as believe on his Name. <hi>Bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt, and the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:188136:56"/>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:188136:56"/>
               <head>The Fourth Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſalm LXXXI. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So I gave them up to their own Hearts lufts: and they walked in their own Counſels.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Come now, in the laſt place, to conſider the Caſe of ſuch, who make <hi>dangerous Approaches</hi> towards ſuch a Judgment; Who have provoked God to that degree, that it would be no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if he ſhould give them up; yea, concerning whom, there is Reaſon to fear it, if ſpeedy Repentance do not prevent.</p>
               <p>HAVING therefore, ſpoken 1. To the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:188136:57"/>Nature of this Judgment, And <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> conſidered the ſteps and Methods, whereby God does ordinarily inflict it, And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the dreadful Severity of it, in Compariſon of any other Judgment in this World; I proceeded to the Caſe of thoſe who <hi>Fear</hi> they are thus left and given up by God: Several Things I named which they alledg as the ground of their <hi>Fear,</hi> which yet will not prove that God hath forſaken 'em: At the ſame time there are many other Things that will evidence the Contrary.</p>
               <p>It remains therefore, that I may faithfully give every one his portion, Comfort to whom Comfort, and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to whom Terrour is due; That I alſo ſpeak to the Caſe of <hi>Such</hi> whoſe Guilt may quickly infer this Terrible Judgment, or concerning whom we may fear, whether they be not already under it, or left of God. There are ſeveral things with relation to this Caſe, which ought to be Conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">I. THE Firſt dangerous Symptom is <hi>Security,</hi> or a Falſe, ungrounded Peace of Conſcience. This is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Prologue, and Forerunner
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:188136:57"/>of Judicial hardning. It is often a part of it, and an Evidence of it Their Caſe therefore is exceeding dangerous, with whom <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a <hi>Aſleep,</hi> or <hi>Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> When that ſin which formerly thy Conſcience would reprove thee for, thou canſt now commit without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, or Difficulty: When ſuch, or ſuch a Luſt can be freely indulged, and thy Heart not reproach thee, thy Conſcience not fly in thy Face, or ſpeak with any ſmartneſs, and Authority againſt it, as formerly it was wont to do: When the Neglect of ſuch or ſuch Duties, was a daily Trouble to thee heretofore, but now thou canſt let <hi>Them alone,</hi> and thy Conſcience will let <hi>Thee alone,</hi> without rebuking thee, or calling thee to Repentance, as it was wont to do. Or if Conſcience do ſpeak, it is with much Faintneſs, without any ſuch Impreſſions of Fear, and ſhame, and ſorrow, as were wont to be produced by it. This ſpeaks as if God had already given thee up in ſome degree, or thou art very near what is worſe, in very great danger of this dreadful Judgment.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Quiet,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the neglect of known Duty,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:188136:58"/>and the Commiſſion of ſin, I grant has it's <hi>Degrees.</hi> There are ſome Degrees of it, into which a good Man, through the Prevalency of ſin and Temptation, for a time may fall. Particularly as to the Duty of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the ſpiritual Performance of it. But then ſuch Perſons, ſuppoſing them Upright in the main, who are under ſuch Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings are far from approving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this Caſe, or from having any ſetled Peace. They have many an unpleaſing Thought about their own Caſe, many Reſolutions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that they may be Recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They often ſay within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>We will go and return to our firſt Husband, for then it was better with us than now;</hi> And every Providence of God, whether of Mercy or Affliction, they regard, as a Call from Heaven to awaken them. And if the Word preached come home to their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Caſe, they receive the Warning, and do not reject it, or oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>But the Perſons I ſpeak of, as in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this Judgment, are ſuch, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially who are <hi>Secure,</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> under the Guilt of great Tranſgreſſions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented of, and under the continued
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:188136:58"/>Omiſſion of plain Duties. They are loſt as to any ſenſe of Sin, and they approve themſelves ſo far in their wretched Courſe, as to ſpeak Peace to themſelves notwithſtanding the repeated and loud Calls, and Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God to repentance.</p>
               <p>Conſcience did formerly ſpeak, but they have ſo long checked, and ſtifled, and diſcouraged, and ſilenced the Voice of Conſcience, as to have loſt one of the greateſt Bleſſings in the World, <hi>viz. Tenderneſs of Conſcience.</hi> They have either ſilenc'd their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by main Force, or they have diſheartened it by a ſlighting, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Carriage; or bribed it by a Form of Godlineſs, an empty barren Profeſſion: And ſo it gives way to a deluſive deſtructive Peace, either to flatter them in the way to Hell, or not truly to inform them of their danger of it.</p>
               <p>Such perſons little Apprehend the danger they are in. For it is much better to have an Awakened Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that roats againſt thee, than a Sleepy, ſilent Conſcience, that doth not reprove thee. It is better thy Conſcience ſhould <hi>not ſpeak a good word</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:188136:59"/>to thee; than, how great cauſe ſoever there be, that it ſhould ſpeak <hi>nothing but good.</hi> That Conſcience ſhould ſpeak <hi>Peace,</hi> when God by his Word ſpeaks <hi>Terrour,</hi> is dreadful in it ſelf, and more ſo, as to what it ſignifies, and has a tendency to.</p>
               <p>Neither is ſuch a Spirit of Slum ber and Security only dangerous, as to the Perſons themſelves, in regard of the State or their own Souls; But theſe ſpiritual Judgments, where they prevail as to great numbers of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtians, (as it is obſerved by many,) are uſually followed with ſome terrible ſtrokes of Temporal Judgment too. For as the firſt and greateſt part of the Deliverance of the Church is <hi>Spiritual,</hi> by the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Divine ſpirit; and the Recovery of the Life and Power of ſerious Religion, and the more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſucceſs of the Goſpel Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and this makes way for publick National Bleſſings, even thoſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind, and is uſually attended with them: So the firſt Entrance into pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick National Judgments, as to <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals,</hi> is by ſpiritual Judgments, on the Body of the People. The abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:188136:59"/>of ſuch ſpiritual Judgments, as we are now ſpeaking of, opens the Door to temporal Calamities, and is the uſual Forerunner of the moſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ones, even of that kind.</p>
               <p>So it was with the old World, ſo with the Jewiſh Nation before their Deſtruction by the Romans; And ſo, ſays <hi>Salvian,</hi> was it with the <hi>African Churches</hi> before the Inundation of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals;</hi> And the like in later Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I believe; among our Neighbours. I wiſh there be no <hi>moral Prognoſtications</hi> of a Day of Evil on this Nation upon the ſame Account. We ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the danger of ſuch a thing, We may on theſe moral grounds very well fear it.</p>
               <p>But it is the Caſe of <hi>Particular Perſons</hi> I have now before me: And the more Security and falſe Peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence any have under great Guilt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented of, or known Duty continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally neglected, the nearer do any ſuch approach to the danger of being giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en up of God to their own Hearts Luſts: If they are not already entered into that diſmal State. And yet how many ſuch bleſs themſelves in their Hearts, and pleaſe themſelves, that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:188136:60"/>they are now free from the Fears of Hell. They do not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about the State of their Souls, as others do, and as they formerly did: They have few or no ſad, and ſerious Thoughts, what ſhall become of them in the Everlaſting World. Of all Others, theſe are <hi>neareſt</hi> to ſuch a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as that in the Text: For <hi>when they ſay Peace and Safety, ſudden Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall overtake them as Travel on a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with Child,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.3. They now ſpeak <hi>Peace</hi> to themſelves, but the next Day or Hour, they may know and feel the Truth of the divine Threatening. That <hi>there is no Peace to the wicked.</hi> There are an hundred threatnings in the Book of God againſt ſuch, and not one Promiſe of ſafety for one Hour. And yet they can lye down, and riſe, and go up and down Securely. They are not afraid when they lye down to ſleep, that they ſhall awake in Hell before the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. They are not afraid when they ariſe and go abroad in the Morning, leſt the Wrath of God ſhould overtake them before Night. Read the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their ſin and Danger in that terrible paſſage, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.18, 20.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:188136:60"/>
               <p n="2">II. ANOTHER Symptom of this Judgment, or dangerous Approach unto it, is when the Miniſtry of the Word, and Goſpel of Chriſt becomes a taſtleſs, inſipid, ineffectual thing; not attended with any ſuch ſpiritual Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as formerly. Heretofore you hardly heard a Sermon without ſome Convictions of ſin, and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it; the Word was quick and powerful, to give an humbling ſenſe of ſin, and to excite your Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to ſet upon neglected Duties; but now there is no ſuch thing. Yea, further, it may be the very exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Worſhip of the Goſpel, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Inſtitutions of it, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencers of them, and they that value and Mind theſe things, are now ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reviled by you; For this is the Caſe of ſome Backſliders, after great Pretences, and an high Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>In ſuch a Caſe you will find your ſpiritual Appetite to the Food of your Souls, (which conſiſts in <hi>Deſires after the ſincere Milk of the word that you may grow thereby,</hi>) to be much abated and loſt; and that Spiritual Savour and Reliſh in the Food of your Souls, which followed thoſe Deſires, is loſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:188136:61"/>too. Your Preparations, Deſires, and Deſigns in coming to ſuch Inſtitutions, are otherwiſe than formerly. Though upon ſome Conſiderations you have not thought fit to abandon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, yet you have no ſuch Appetite or Taſt, no ſuch Deſires, and no ſuch Reliſh, as to theſe things, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you had. Neither do you of late experience any of thoſe excellent Effects, which the Diſpenſation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is deſigned to produce upon the Minds, and Conſciences, and Lives of Men. Though there is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the degree of theſe Declenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet this is the high Road to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration, Hardneſs of Heart and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Impenitence. And therefore, to uſe the Words of a learned Perſon concerning ſuch Apoſtates,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen, <hi>Dominion of ſin and Grace, p.</hi> 89.</note> 
                  <q>The Calls of God unto ſuch Backſliders in heart, for a return by Repentance, are multiplied, and the Reaſons of it are innumerable; and without it, it is certain, that they ſhall periſh Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and they know not how ſoon they may be overtaken with that Deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:188136:61"/>often reproved, hardens his Heart, ſhall ſuddenly be destroyed, and that without Remedy.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If Men once come to this, that, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt ſearching, lively Sermons, they can continue ſecure, and wilful in known ſins; they may fear leſt they be left to go further; even to the hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Godlineſs, and good Men; Or at leaſt to be ſo far ſtupified, as not to feel any thing of the force of Gods Terrors, or the ſweetneſs of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; but to make a Jeſt of ſin, and think a Life of Godlineſs a needleſs thing. Such Perſons, when it comes to this, eſpecially if they grow old in this Courſe, have Cauſe to fear leſt they be forſaken of God, and given over to their own Hearts Luſts, ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up under Judicial Blindneſs, and Hardneſs of Heart.</p>
               <p n="3">III. WHEN The Spirit of Grace gives over ſtriving with the Souls of Men. This is a moſt dangerous Caſe: For except He return, they are irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably loſt. There is an abſolute neceſſity of the Influence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit to the Begining, Progreſs, and Continuance of the Spiritual Life;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:188136:62"/>and there is no Oppoſition in the Soul, but this Spirit of Life and Power can overcome. But when he gives over ſtriving with men how deplorable muſt their Caſe be! And this he doth with many, after they have reſiſted <hi>the</hi> Spirit, and rebelled againſt the Spirit, and vexed the Holy Spirit of God, as we read of ſome that did, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. Now if this bleſſed Spirit move not upon the Soul of <hi>a Backſlider,</hi> he can never be recovered. And when he hath often been repulſed and grieved, and quenched, he may withdraw in Anger; and God may juſtly reſolve, as concerning the old World, that his Spirit ſhall ſtrive no more, no longer with them.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially when after a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity, men turn Apoſtates, and deſpiſe Preaching, and the other Inſtitutions of the Goſpel; having <hi>done deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, Heb.</hi> 10.29. Which, though ſpoken of open, final Apoſtates, ſhould make Others that approach thereto to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>And of how much ſoever Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall ſuch be thought guilty,</hi> that do thus Deſpight to the Spirit of Chriſt, who bears Witneſs to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:188136:62"/>and Doctrine! Who can tell the Dreadfulneſs and Horrour of their Puniſhment? The Conſtitution of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> reached but to a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Death without mercy: But beſides temporal. Judgments, ſuch a Guilt will expoſe them to Eternal Wrath; For the greateſt ſin will have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>No wonder then if the Holy Spirit ſtrive no more with Perſons that come under this tremendous Guilt; that ſin againſt the Holy Spirit, even as <hi>a Spirit of Grace;</hi> doing Deſpight to the Spirit of Grace, who did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, and wooe, and draw them unto Chriſt, to bring them under the Bond of the Covenant. <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alway ſtrive with men, Gen.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 13 7. When the Spirit of Grace, and Love, and Benignity, hath ſhone in upon their Minds, and often touched their Conſciences; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly whiſpered, <hi>Sinner,</hi> Wilt thou not yet turn? What, haſt thou no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to return to me? O do not go on and periſh, &amp;c. Now to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pight this very Spirit of Grace, muſt needs be attended with great Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:188136:63"/>of Guilt, becauſe it is after ſome Experience of his Influence and Power. This muſt be one of the moſt dangerous Symptoms of a periſhing loſt Condition: The Goſpel muſt needs be hid unto ſuch, becauſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Light and Influence of the Holy Spirit, it can have no ſaving Effect. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, ſays</hi> our Apoſtle, <hi>it is hid to them that are lost,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.3. <hi>Whoſe Minds are blinded by Satan, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine into their Hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though I muſt here add, that no Man, I believe, can determine, what Degree of this Guilt as to particular Perſons, doth diſtinguiſh thoſe who are <hi>Irrecoverably lost,</hi> from ſuch as are <hi>Recoverable,</hi> and may be called to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. THOUGH The Spirit have not done ſtriving; yet when the preaching of the Word, though you cannot reſiſt the Light of divine Truth, but ſomewhat of it ſhines into the Mind and Conſcience; if yet <hi>your Hearts</hi> ſtand out, and will not yield, this is a dangerous Caſe. For men
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:188136:63"/>may be convinced by the Word, of the ſinfulneſs and Danger of their Condition; they may come to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and to pronounce Judgment upon themſelves, that what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of them is but Juſt and equal, and that hitherto they have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with his Call. One thing or other, from day to day, hath hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from coming up to the terms of the Goſpel, from a covenant Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with the Son of God upon the Goſpel Call: They may ſay, and own it before God and Men, <q>That they are deeply convinced ſuch a thing ought to be done; But I have not yet found the time, or the Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the Heart, to retire into a Cloſet, and conſider it, and ſet about it in good earneſt, and give up my Soul to him; I am convinced I muſt do it, or I cannot enter into Heaven; I am convinced I muſt turn, or I ſhall dye; I am ſatisfied this my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Courſe muſt iſſue in my Ruine, my Eternal Ruine; that if I go on and dye in this Caſe,</q> I am loſt for ever. But yet, notwithſtanding ſuch Convictions, with many, ſtill <hi>the Heart</hi> holds out againſt all that can be ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:188136:64"/>
               <p>The higheſt and the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant matters that can be named, though propounded with the cleareſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and repreſented as of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Concern to them, yet do not effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prevail with them. Though we propoſe, in the Name of God, the Incouragment of that Bleſſedneſs, and Priviledge, which no man, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands and believes, but muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; Though we flaſh the Fire of Hell before them, and endeavour by the Terrors of the Lord to perſwade them; yet they have heard of theſe things ſo often, that they are not mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them to yield themſelves to the Lord. All that we ſpeak in the Name of Chriſt is as a Tale that is told, they have heard it ſo often it makes little Impreſſion: Things are come to that ſad paſs with them, and they are Scrmon-proof to that Degree, that (to uſe the words of a Great man,) unleſs we could ſpeak of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er things than <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> we cannot move them. And though their Minds are inlightened, and ſome Convictions begun; yet their Luſts carry the Day againſt their Convictions: Conſcience is baffled,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:188136:64"/>or kept under by the Power of vicious Inclinations.</p>
               <p>And while men go on at this rate, who can tell but God may ſay, <hi>Let them alone?</hi> but that he may give them up to thoſe Luſts they have choſen, and ſo their Condition be deſperate: Though they themſelves do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it to be ſo? And as to indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Perſons we cannot diſtinctly tell when it is ſo; but ſo <hi>it may be,</hi> and God be clear in his Righteouſneſs herein: becauſe it is penal, and after great Provocations, and it was lately other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with them: But they ſinned away their Mercy, and outſtood their Day. There was a time when he would have been found of them, but now he will not. <hi>O that thou hadſt known in this thy day the things that</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto thy Peace! <hi>Now they are hid from thine Eyes:</hi> A little while ago they were not.</p>
               <p>But to prevent miſtake, Remember, that though the Spirit retiring from ſuch, does infer their Day of Grace to be paſt, <hi>if he return not;</hi> and for ought you can tell, <hi>he never may;</hi> yet he doth not Darken their Minds by putting any ill thoughts into them, or any
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:188136:65"/>ill Diſpoſition of Mind. God retires, and the Spirit leaves you, after you have provoked him, and ſo you are loſt. He only ſays, <q>This wretched Creature will not be prevailed with, he perſiſts in a careleſs Neglect of me, and my Son and Spirit; we will leave him, and let him alone to his own Luſts, to walk in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</q> 
                  <hi>O dreadful Doom!</hi> how ſhould the Danger of it ſtartle us!</p>
               <p n="5">V. THERE are Others, whoſe Caſe is exceeding dangerous, who, after ſome trial in the ways of God, for want of that ſenſible Joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which they expected, grow wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, and leave them off. They were formerly diligent, and conſtant in the outward performance of ſuch and ſuch Duties of Worſhip, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and private; but now have laid them aſide. Some of theſe, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, have now and then a ſentence of Condemnation within themſelves, but Others are hardened paſt feeling. They tried a while, and began hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and made a little Progreſs; But their Convictions did not preſently end in peace of Conſcience, they did
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:188136:65"/>not preſently meet with that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſettlement, and Eſtabliſhment which they hoped for; either through their own Ignorance, or want of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Counſel concerning the ſtate of their Souls, or from the Power of Temptation, &amp;c. But not finding <hi>ſuch</hi> Peace and Joy as they expected, or <hi>ſo ſoon,</hi> they give over, and go back to their wonted Courſe of ſin, and Neglect of God.</p>
               <p>This is the Caſe of many convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in their Youth.</hi> They follow the Tendency of that for ſome time, they hope for a good Iſſue, and that their Trouble of Soul will be quickly over: They pray and read, and confeſs ſin, and mourn for it, &amp;c. But find not preſently the Peace they expected, they find their Luſts to ſtrive and ſtir ſtill, and ſin and <hi>Satan</hi> not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and it may be ſome Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are more ſtrong than formerly, or they are more ſenſible of their ſtrength, and Acting: Hereupon the Devil ſuggeſts to them matter of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragment, and their own Hearts are ready to make them ſay, in a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Deſpondency of Spirit, <q>I ſee I am entered into a melancholy
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:188136:66"/>courſe of Life; I ſee no end of theſe Troubles, I fear I ſhall never attain to Peace as long as I hearken to my Conſcience: If I thus let every ſin trouble me, I ſhall never have a days Quiet: If I am thus nice, and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, and tender about ſin and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſhall never while I live get out of theſe Perplexities. Therefore I will even caſt all off, I will give my ſelf more Liberty, and hearken to my Conſcience no longer; I will take my Pleaſure as I ſee others do, and not wait any longer for thoſe Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of another kind, which I was told of, but deſpair of attaining. I give up all for loſt, as to any of theſe things, I ſhall never reach them; therefore I will do as well as I can for the preſent; I will drive away my melancholy Thoughts by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and Wine, and Mirth, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon ſuch Perſons come in a little while to diſlike all ſuch Books, and Preaching as would revive their Convictions, and to avoid the very Company of thoſe who knew any thing of the ſtate of their Souls, while under Conviction, and are like to ſpeak to them about it. That Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:188136:66"/>that will not let them alone, and ſuffer them to be quiet in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Luſts, they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; and in a little while they care for none at all; unleſs their Credit, and Reputation, or Temporal Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, or ſome ſuch Motive, ingage them to attend it. Or elſe they cure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſome falſe Doctrines, that put an end to their Convictions, and make them eaſily perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they are <hi>Elected,</hi> and that <hi>Christ is theirs,</hi> and their <hi>Sins</hi> are <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned,</hi> or were <hi>ſo</hi> from all Eternity, &amp;c. But this is a hazardous and dreadful Caſe, when Perſons arrive to this pitch, they had need look about them, and Return quickly, leſt God ſhould give them over.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. WHEN men continue in ſin, and put off their Repentance and Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, with this Thought and Intention, that <hi>they will ſome time or other Repent,</hi> and turn to God, but <hi>not yet.</hi> One can hardly tell, whether the provoking <hi>Guilt,</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> of ſuch a Caſe, be greater than the horrid <hi>Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> of it. And yet this is a Deluſion that has ruined Thouſands, and made
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:188136:67"/>ample Harveſts for the Devil. They have ſome Tremblings under the Word, as <hi>Felix</hi> when the Apoſtle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of Righteouſneſs, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and Judgment to come; But <hi>the convenient time</hi> for their complying with their Convictions, and performing their good Reſolutions, is not come, but they intend it, they reſolve it.</p>
               <p>I would fain ask ſuch Perſons, that now continue in known ſin, unrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, who yet <hi>intend to Repent;</hi> whether they indeed think that God <hi>will Accept,</hi> and forgive them when they do Repent, or that he <hi>will not?</hi> If they ſay, as doubtleſs they will, We think and hope <hi>he will</hi> forgive us, and whenever we truly Repent, he has promiſed to receive us. Yet,</p>
               <p n="1">1. IS it not then the baſeſt, and the moſt horrid Ingratitude that can be, to continue longer to abuſe the Grace of God, to aſſront him, and rebel againſt him, and delay your Return to him, with this Thought? Dare you ſay to the God of all Grace, who has born with you ſo long, <q>
                     <hi>Lord,</hi> I have diſhonoured thy Name for ſo many years, I have ſlighted thy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I have diſobeyed thy Calls, I have refuſed thy Grace, I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:188136:67"/>my ſelf to thy righteous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger all my Life hitherto; O let me alone to do ſo <hi>thus much longer,</hi> and then I will Repent, then I will ask thee forgiveneſs.</q> How ungrateful, how abſurd is ſuch a Speech!</p>
               <p n="2">2. WILL Not the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that keeps thee from Repenting now, be as ſtrong hereafter? For after all the little objections againſt Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Reforming at preſent; the only one at the bottom is, <hi>becauſe it is Preſent;</hi> and that will ſtill hold: So that your Turning to God will be as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable at any time hereafter, as now.</p>
               <p>It ought to be very well conſidered in this Caſe, That whoever continues in ſin with this Thought, and Deſign of <hi>Repenting hereafter;</hi> the Devil is ſure to proſper in any Attempt againſt that Man. For when that time comes to be <hi>preſent,</hi> unto which he has adjourned his intended Repentance, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be <hi>as ſtrong</hi> againſt repenting <hi>then,</hi> as it is for delaying <hi>now.</hi> He will then adjourn it to ſome diſtance ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. DO You know what <hi>Repentance</hi> is, that you will venture upon ſin with a Deſign to Repent? That is, that you will continue to do that, which
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:188136:68"/>you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſolve and intend, to wiſh you had never done; to be heartily ſorry that you were ſuch Fools as to do it. You reſolve to do that, which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to be aſhamed of, and to loath your ſelves for, and would give all the World, if it were in your Power that you had not done it: For this is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in <hi>Repentance.</hi> Now is it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wiſdom, and Reaſon of a Man, thus to act?</p>
               <p n="4">4. ART Thou ſure to live to that time, unto which thou delayeſt thy Repentance, and Turning to God? With how many every week is that the Caſe, who intend to Repent, <hi>ſome time</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> but dye before the time comes?</p>
               <p n="6">VI. WHAT If God ſhould give thee over to thine own Hearts Luſts? May he not juſtly leave thee to the hardneſs of thine impenitent Heart? Doth not ſuch a Carriage of thine deſerve it? If thou wilt go on from Month to Month, from year to year, in the neglect of known Duties, under the Convictions of Conſcience, that thou art not yet turned to God, or recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iled to him; thou wilt, <hi>I ſay,</hi> yet go on,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:188136:68"/>and continue as thou art, though thy Heart tell thee, if thou dye in this Condition thou muſt periſh; and thou haſt nothing to relieve thee in this ſad Caſe, but only an Intention <hi>to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſome time hereafter:</hi> O how Juſtly may God deny that Grace to <hi>Thee,</hi> which thou haſt ſo long abuſed, and forfeited, and wilt not now Accept! How righteouſly mayſt thou be ſealed up to Deſtruction, by Gods forſaking of thee!</p>
               <p n="7">VII. THERE is another ſort, whoſe Caſe is exceeding dangerous, <hi>viz.</hi> Who often fall into the ſame ſins, which they Repent of, and are ſorry for. After they have ſinned, they Repent of thoſe ſins again; and after ſome Repentance, they commit the ſame ſins again; and ſo have the Aggravations of ſinning againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Now <hi>to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not;</hi> that knoweth what is evil, and forbears it not, <hi>to him it is ſin</hi> with a Witneſs, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7. <hi>He that knew his Maſters Will, and did it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes, Luk.</hi> 12.49.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:188136:69"/>
               <p>It is a dreadful paſſage, though ſpoken of Apoſtates from the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity unto Judaiſm or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 26, 27, 28, 29. That <hi>ſuch as ſin after the Knowledg of the Truth, there remains no more ſacrifice for ſuch ſins.</hi> For what further Guilt may not ſuch ſins againſt Knowledge bring them to, and iſſue in? Doubtleſs the more you know, and have conſidered the Iſſue and Conſequence of ſuch ſins, (as by renewing your Repentance is impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſomething of this kind has been done;) the more aggravated is your Sin afterward, and the more dangerous your Caſe. And the more ſtruggle and ſtriving there has been of Conſcience againſt Corruption; and yet thy Luſts have carried the day and got the victory over Conſcience; The more Vows and Promiſes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment that you have made, and broken, and ſinned againſt; repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Repentance, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> did; the greater is your ſin and Danger: The more Warnings you have had of God by his Providence, and the more awakening Calls of his Word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yet you continue this Courſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ning, and repenting, of repenting,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:188136:69"/>and ſinning ſtill; the more dangerous is your Caſe. Eſpecially under a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſon of Religion. For in a little time Conſcience thus affronted is like enough to be hardened, and <hi>to be ſeared as with an hot Iron,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.12. And God may give you up to an impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Heart, leaving you to commit the groſſeſt Abominations, without ſhame or Remorſe, as he did the Gentiles, <hi>Rom</hi> 1.21, 24, 26, 28.</p>
               <p>If ſuch be ever awakened to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in this World, this very Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration will pierce them to the Heart; this will make them ready to deſpair; That, as the Apoſtle ſaid of himſelf, <hi>I did it ignorantly, therefore I obtained Mercy;</hi> They will be ready to cry out againſt themſelves, I did ſo and ſo, but it was <hi>againſt Knowledge,</hi> therefore there is <hi>no Mercy</hi> for me. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for ſuch, without Repentance a moſt fearful Puniſhment, And a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful looking for, and Expectation of ſuch Puniſhment, in the Conſciences of thoſe who have ſinned at this rate. And there be very Few of thoſe who have lived long under the preaching of the Word, and continued to ſin thus againſt Knowledge, and Conſcience
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:188136:70"/>till they were old; <hi>very few ſuch</hi> are recovered to Repentance. Certainly the greater the <hi>Knowledge</hi> is you ſin againſt the more you provoke God to give you up to a reprobate Mind, and to leave you to hardneſs of Heart.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. WHEN, Notwithſtanding the Profeſſion of Religion, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Attendance on the Duties of it, yet ſin has the Dominion and Maſtery in the Soul; and ſenſual Inclinations are indulged without reſtraint, even as to groſs and notorious ſins. There are ſome Backſliders, who would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly have ſtarted back at ſuch or ſuch a Temptation, who can now boldly enter into it, readily yield, and are eaſily overcome, without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern or ſtruggle. Sin has the Maſtery and Dominion in the Soul, they go on to commit it without Check or Fear. They conſent to its Rule, they are willing ſubjects: For <hi>to whom you yield your Servants to obey, his Servants ye are, Rom.</hi> 6.6. And that victory which Sin hath got by your own Conſent, may juſtly, as it commonly doth in the ſwent, bring that Bondage and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:188136:70"/>under ſin, which is <hi>Judicial,</hi> and <hi>Penal.</hi> That ſlavery to ſin which at firſt was <hi>voluntary,</hi> afterwards becomes <hi>unavoidable.</hi> You are held in the Chains of your own ſins, you are cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated and ovrecome by your own luſts. <hi>While they promiſe themſelves Liberty,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>they are the Servants of Corruption: for of whom a Man is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, of the ſame is he brought into Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>There is leſs hope of ſuch Men that are grown looſe and ſenſual, after they have been forward Profeſſors: And they are harder to be recovered than any others. For they are more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be left of God. Some have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily ſaid, that an open profligate debauched Perſon is <hi>nearer</hi> the Grace of God and ſalvation by Chriſt, than <hi>a moral honeſt Man,</hi> that is kept from the groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Pollutions of the World. But ſuch Expreſſions ſhould not make us think, that God will invite and wooe us the more earneſtly, the further our ſins have divorced us from him.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammonds <hi>Sermons, p.</hi> 275.</note> It is true, the Holy Ghoſt can cleanſe and adorn, and prepare himſelf a room
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:188136:71"/>in any Heart, and ſoften it, and not be repulſed by the moſt habituate ſin, or Devil. And ſome have been thus ſnatched like fire-brands out of the Fire, and changed from incarnate Devils to incarnate Saints. Yet thoſe extraordinary and rare Examples muſt not be thought a Rule. Therefore in ordinary charitable Reaſon, we ought to Judge more hopefully of thoſe Men, who have not run into the groſſeſt ſenſualities, and Corruptions of the World; of ſuch eſpecially, who by any common Influence of the Spirit, with the Word, have been kept back from great Tranſgreſſions; ſo that by the Knowledge of Chriſt, they have eſcaped the Pollutions of the World; and by the Advantage of their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and common Grace, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, have been reſtrained from foul Miſcarriages. If ſuch as theſe do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards become profane, and looſe, and ſenſual, and groſly carnal; it is ſaid of them, <hi>their latter End is like to be worſe than their Begining. And it had been better for them not to have known the Way of Righteouſneſs, than, after having known it, to turn from the holy Commandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſome Men may ſin them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:188136:71"/>into a ſtate of <hi>Incurable Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> is very plain from Scripture. Your neglect and Provocations may put Chriſt to his Irreverſible Oath, and make him ſwear as he once did, that <hi>you ſhall not enter into his</hi> Reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.11. And that this is of force in the times of the Goſpel, is more than inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, <hi>v.</hi> 12. Exhorting profeſſing Chriſtians at that time, to beware of <hi>an Evil heart of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> That Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9. Is quoted no leſs than <hi>ſix times</hi> in the New Taſtament, as if it belonged to them, who ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Goſpel Light.</p>
               <p>As to that difficult paſſage, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5. Concerning thoſe <hi>who had been made Partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and taſted of the good Word of God, and of the Powers of the World to come, and yet did fall away;</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>it is impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new them again.</hi> In the ordinary way it is not to be expected. Though that Paſſage do eſpecially reſpect ſuch Apoſtates as openly renounced Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, crucifying the Son of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh: Yet ſuch as, after a plauſible Profeſſion, turn to a looſe and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wicked Life, whether they keep
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:188136:72"/>that Profeſſion ſtill, or abandon it, they are greatly in danger of the like Judgment. <hi>For the Earth that drinks in the Rain that often comes upon it, and yet brings forth nothing but Briars, is rejected, and is nigh unto Curſing, whoſe end is to be burned,</hi> as it there follows, 7, 8. <hi>V.</hi> Their Caſe is next to hopeleſs and deſperate. And what reaſon have all Backſliders to fear, leſt they ſin them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſuch a diſmal ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. And let that be the firſt Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I would make of this Diſcourſe, To awaken <hi>Apostates,</hi> and <hi>Backſliders</hi> to Conſider their Danger. It may be you have gratified your Luſts, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Light of Conſcience, and the Motions of the Spirit; Now, it may be, you can ſin with leſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, and don't feel the Wounds you give your ſelves by your Tranſgreſſions? Can you ſay but that the Bleſſed Spirit is retired in great meaſure already? And is it any Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, after ſo many ſtruggles and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, if he ſhould for ever Retire, and leave you to the full uncontroulable Dominion of your own Luſts? If he ſhould ſay, <hi>he that is filthy, let him be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thy ſtill; becauſe you would not bepurged,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:188136:72"/>you ſhall not be purged, till I make my Fury to reſt upon you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Awake therefore, and conſider your Danger. You that find any of theſe things agree to your own Caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leſt you be in the Number of thoſe <hi>that draw back unto Perdition,</hi> in whom <hi>God ſays his Soul can take no Pleaſure, Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Take no Pleaſure,</hi> that is, whom he loaths, and deteſts. Were we not under ſome great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion, ſome ſad degree of Hardneſs of Heart our ſelves; how ſhould we pity the Caſe of all ſuch Perſons who are near this Judgment? With what hearty Concern for them, ſhould we endeavour their Recovery, did we know better, and believingly conſider more, what it is to be left of God, and given over! With what hearty Grief ſhould I mourn over ſuch Perſons! With what Groans, and Tears of Compaſſion ſhould I warn them, and try to awaken them, if my own Heart were not under ſomwhat of <hi>this Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> which they are like to be totally given up unto!</p>
               <p>I confeſs, at firſt, I was loth to preach, or publiſh theſe things, leſt I ſhould drive ſome <hi>to Deſpair.</hi> But upon more
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:188136:73"/>ſerious Conſideration, I do not think that the Generality of People are ſo very apt to <hi>Deſpair.</hi> They have ten thouſand ways to <hi>flatter</hi> themſelves, and <hi>they will hope</hi> for the moſt part, in deſpight of all Arguments to the Contrary. In all the Scripture there is but <hi>one Example</hi> of a deſpairing Man, and that was <hi>Judas;</hi> Who did not deſpair by reaſon of any terrible Doctrine which was preached to him, but becauſe of the Load of his own foul ſin and the Weakneſs and Puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity of his own Spirit. But for <hi>one</hi> who deſpairs, O what <hi>Multitudes</hi> are there who live in ſin, and yet <hi>Sibi ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter benedicunt,</hi> think themſelves in a good Condition, and that all is well; Though the Scriptures ſay, that the Righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved, and that the Gate is ſtraight that leads to Life; yet every Body almoſt hopes to be ſaved, in the Courſe they are in, though it be the broad way.</p>
               <p>YOU that are under any of theſe dangerous Symptoms that approach to ſuch a Judgment, take heed of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging your ſelves in <hi>a falſe Hope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vation.</hi> Bethink your ſelves, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd your Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger, and awake to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:188136:73"/>prevent the diſmal Iſſue. Make haſte, and eſcape for your Life, if yet there be Hope of your Recovery. It muſt be ſpeedy Repentance, <hi>now,</hi> while it is called to day, before the Maſter of the Houſe be gone, and <hi>the Door ſhut:</hi> For then <hi>many ſhall ſeek to enter, and ſhall not be able.</hi> For ſo we read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24, 25, Verſes connected, without a full ſtop between them, as in our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation.</p>
               <p>If you are not yet ſealed up, and given over, (as the Motions of the Spirit yet ſtriving with you, and ſome Concernedneſs about your own Caſe, is a good Argument that you are not) O awake, and call upon God! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering whence you are fallen, and repent preſently: For if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and refuſe <hi>this Call</hi> of God, you may never have <hi>Another,</hi> or never have <hi>Grace</hi> to hearken to another, and then the Iſſue will be the ſame.</p>
               <p>I would hope, that none of thoſe to whom I now ſpeak are ſo <hi>Loſt</hi> but they may be <hi>Recovered</hi> (And I cannot think that any who reads this, is in ſo hopeleſs a Caſe, but he may find Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, if yet he will ſeek it.) <hi>He has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſinned the ſin unto Death, who is afraid left
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:188136:74"/>he be guilty of it</hi> You are not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given over and forſaken of God, or ſure that you ſhall finally be ſo, that this Spirit will no more return, though in ſome Degree you are forſaken; If you are brought to conſider your Danger, and to reſolve to uſe Means to prevent the fatal Iſſue: You are not finally left of God, whatever dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Approaches you have made to ſuch a Judgment. In the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of your Danger, awake to uſe Gods appointed Means. And here,</p>
               <p n="1">1. I might adviſe, that you Watch carefully leſt you enter into Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2. That you take heed of ſlight Thoughts of ſin. 3. That you labour to have right Apprehenſions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Attributes of God, and the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the New Covenant by Chriſt Jeſus. 4. That you attend the Miniſtry of the Word, with a Deſire and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſome ſpiritual Advantage, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your own Caſe. Take heed of being ſlight and careleſs in the uſe of thoſe Means, that muſt cure a hard Heart, if ever it be cured. 5. In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all Means, look up to God for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Influence of the divine Spirit. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:188136:74"/>the Neceſſity of it, for the Cure of a hard or backſliding Heart. 6. Call your ſelves often to an Account how matters ſtand between God and you. 7. Ingage more heartily, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and conſtantly in the uſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Prayer. 8. Improve the ſickneſs and Death of others, as Warnings to awaken the Thoughts of your own. 9. In any Doubt and Difficulty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (eſpecially under Temptations to Deſpair,) do not ſcruple to open your Caſe to ſome faithful Miniſter of Chriſt, that may enlighten and and guide you. 10. Labour to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand diſtinctly what that <hi>Repentance towards God is,</hi> and that <hi>Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which are the ſtated Terms of Life, and the Condition of the new Covenant. And never give over the uſe of Means, till you are brought to Repent of all your ſins againſt God, and truly to believe in Jeſus Chriſt with all your Heart; evidencing your unfeigned Faith by new Obedience. Therefore take heed by what <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Signs</hi> you Judge your ſelves, leſt all your Soul Trouble ſhould end in a falſe Peace.</p>
               <p>I connot conclude without repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:188136:75"/>the Admonition againſt that <hi>falſe Peace,</hi> which one great Work of our Miniſtry is to deſtroy. For there are Multitdes of People who pretend to love God, and to love good Men, and to truſt in Chriſt that he dyed for them, and to rely on Chriſt, and to caſt themſelves on Chriſt, and think they believe on him, and that they ſhall be ſaved. Who will tell you that as for Obedience, they mind it as they can, though they be not as good as others; their <hi>Hearts</hi> are good, and they mean well, and they know their own Hearts better than Miniſters do: they are ſure they believe in Chriſt; and they will conclude that all is well, &amp;c. Tho 'tis notorious of <hi>Many ſuch,</hi> that they are Ignorant of God, and ſtrangers to Chriſt, and live in the common allowed practice of great ſins. Yet they will thus <hi>Hope well</hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſpeak Peace to themſelves.</p>
               <p>NO Wonder if they do ſo <hi>now,</hi> when even at the Day of Judgment ſome are brought in diſputing with Chriſt, till the Heart of their Hopes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> broken by his condemning Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce. Not as if thoſe that now dye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enitence and Unbelief, ſhould
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:188136:75"/>not know, or believe that they ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh for ever, till after the general Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But matters ſeem there to be repreſented, as applied to the Perſons of thoſe who ſhall be found alive at the End of this World, or whoſe Eternal State in the next World is concluded, by what their Caſe is when they leave this ſtate of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>SEE Therefore that your <hi>Hopes</hi> be of a right Kind, grounded on Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Evidence, pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fying the Heart, conquering the World, exciting thy Deſires after Chriſt and Heaven, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee to ſin leſs, and to pleaſe and glorifie God more. Such an Hope you may hold faſt, it will not make you aſhamed. But of all things fear <hi>a falſe Hope.</hi> Dread it as you would the ſin of <hi>Deſpair;</hi> yea as the moſt danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the two, becauſe more common. I mean not <hi>a Deſpair</hi> of the ſufficiency and Willingneſs of Chriſt to pardon and ſave thee, if thou repent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and obey him; Nor a <hi>Deſpair</hi> of finding Mercy, if thou heartily ſeek it. But <hi>deſpair</hi> thou muſt of ever ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God without Holineſs. <hi>Deſpair</hi> that Chriſt will ever be the Author of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:188136:76"/>eternal Salvation to any, but ſuch as believe and obey him: <hi>Deſpair</hi> of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping Eternal Death if thou live after the Fleſh: <hi>Deſpair</hi> of entering into Heaven if thou wilt not ſeek it in the firſt place: <hi>Deſpair</hi> of eſcaping the Doom of periſhing with the Ungodly, except you ſoundly Repent, except you turn to God, and Holineſs, from ſin and the World; except you peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently and thankfully accept of Chriſt, obey and follow him as your Lord and Saviour. <hi>Deſpair</hi> therefore of ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved in the ſtate thou art in, with whom it is not thus.</p>
               <p>GOD will ere long deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with thee, and let thee know the Truth. And what will it avail thy periſhing Soul, for Miniſters to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and flatter thee with vain <hi>Hopes;</hi> when, without Repentance and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God in Chriſt, there is none? Nay if any thing keep thee out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (I ſpeak of the Caſe of moſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Hearers, and Profeſſors,) If any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing keep thee out of Heaven, it is <hi>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe and groundleſs Hope</hi> of coming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er.</p>
               <p>CHRISTIANS, We muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeak plain. Would you have
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:188136:76"/>us be unfaithful to God and you: We muſt be accountable to God ere long, as well as you: We muſt ſtand before his Judgment ſeat as well as you. Why ſhould we give you <hi>Hopes,</hi> if God do give you <hi>none?</hi> I therefore ſay it again, that, without ſpeedy and ſincere Repentance towards God, and Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, evidenced by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial faithful Obedience to him, there is no Hope, for any one of you. And they that hear often of theſe things, and will yet go on in ſin; it is Juſt with God to leave them, and give them up to their own Hearts Luſt. Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> away your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, return to the Lord with all your Hearts, and yield your ſelves to the Claim, and Call of Chriſt <hi>without Delay,</hi> while Mercy invites you, and Grace may be had, for <hi>why will you Dye, O Houſe of Iſrael?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:77"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Chandler.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Mourners Companion,</hi> or Funeral Diſcourſes from ſeveral Texts, 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> price bound 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Death a Deliverance,</hi> in a Funeral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. fit to bind with the Mourners Companion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacramental Diſcourſes</hi> on ſeveral Texts before and after <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Lords Prayer, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, 1<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Practical Relfection</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes</hi> in <hi>Jamaica <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Malta, &amp;c.</hi> With a Particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Account of thoſe, and <hi>Divers</hi> other <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, price bound 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious Reflections</hi> on <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> with ſome other Subjects Moral and Divine, to which is Annexed an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix concerning the firſt Day of the year, how obſerved by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and may beſt be employed by a ſerious Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>All five by Mr. <hi>John Shower.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:188136:78"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
